<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Security on Salman Quazi</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/tags/security/</link><description>Recent content in Security on Salman Quazi</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>Salman Quazi</managingEditor><lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 13:13:32 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.salmanq.com/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to check if Integrated Windows Authentication is available?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/how-to-check-if-integrated-windows-authentication-is-available/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 13:13:32 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/how-to-check-if-integrated-windows-authentication-is-available/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked on an intranet site, you often want to know, programmatically, if a client that&amp;rsquo;s accessing your website has the ability to automatically login to your site (Integrated Windows Authentication). With Integration Windows Authentication, Windows can basically send (as a HTTP header) the currently &amp;ldquo;logged on&amp;rdquo; username. So your application can access this LOGON_USER HTTP header and go from there. I won&amp;rsquo;t get into the details of how to setup integrated windows authentication, but basically the idea is you go into IIS and for a given resource (a folder or a file) on your site you change the directory security to Integrated Windows Authentication. Once this is done, when a client visits your local site (the definition of local depends on the gateway or group policy), IE switches to the &amp;ldquo;intranet site&amp;rdquo; profile which allows the automatic authentication. That&amp;rsquo;s the broad picture. But unfortunately, if the same users visits that same website from another location, say from their home, they will end up getting the ugly NTLM authentication box - and most of the times they don&amp;rsquo;t know what to do. Partly because their experience has changed, at work they were simply &amp;ldquo;logged in&amp;rdquo; without doing anything and now they have to login and often times need to prefix their username with domain username format. That&amp;rsquo;s not good. So it&amp;rsquo;s useful to be able to find out programmatically if integrated windows authentication is available, if it is then you simply login using the integration authentication, otherwise you provide the user with a clean and simple forms authentication system. So let&amp;rsquo;s start with some JavaScript code:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>CTRL+ALT+DEL Twice?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/ctrlaltdel-twice/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2005 04:21:46 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/ctrlaltdel-twice/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In Windows XP pressing CTRL+ALT+DEL twice in the login screen will take you to the classic login screen where you can manually type in the username and password to authenticate yourself. &lt;a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/oldnewthing/archive/2005/09/14/466051.aspx"&gt;According to a Microsoft employee&lt;/a&gt; this feature maybe removed in future releases of Windows or worst yet it might be removed in future service packs. This would have caused serious problems for me because non-of the users I have on the intial list are administrators to the system. That means without that feature I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been able to login to the computer as an administrator (&lt;em&gt;unless I did run-as on computer management MMC and made myself administrator and then loged as me again&lt;/em&gt;). But just a note that whoever is depending on this should be aware!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using ASP.NET to authenticate against AD</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-asp-net-to-authenticate-against-ad/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2005 02:58:44 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-asp-net-to-authenticate-against-ad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The company I work for reliies heavily on active-directory to organize, authenticate and integrate. In order to login to the intranet from our site, we currently request the integrated windows authentication box and ask the user to login. For some people this was a little flattering because it didn&amp;rsquo;t really say why the login was taking place &amp;ndash; where are they loging into and so on. So to remedy this issue, I am working on a ASP.NET product that will authenticate against AD. This can be done using DirectoryServices provided within the .NET framework.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>FTP &amp; Microsoft ISA Server 2004</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/ftp-microsoft-isa-server-2004/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2005 13:31:57 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/ftp-microsoft-isa-server-2004/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/isaserver/default.mspx"&gt;Microsoft ISA (Internet Security and Acceleration Server) 2004&lt;/a&gt; is a tool to secure and accelerate (as the name suggests) networks running on Windows platforms. It&amp;rsquo;s a very powerful tool and is one of the most flexible firewalls I have seen in the market. Where I work, Microsoft ISA actually replaced several CISCO firewalls. Not only were we able to migrate all the access lists rules we were able to do far more than that. Just so we a sense of our setup we have two Microsoft ISA servers running. One that handles the X subnet and the handles the Y subnet. All of the servers and static-IP workstations are hosted on the Y subnet. The ISA server that firewalls the Y subnet allows more incoming and outgoing ports to facilitate testing, production level data transfer and so on. Me and our system administrators spent almost all day today trying to figure out a solution to a strange problem. When we FTP from the Y subnet (the static subnet) to a external box, we can successfully login because PORT 21 is port. However, after logging in we cannot upload any files. After some researching I found out that FTP does not receive data from PORT 21 but changes the incoming port dynamically which is set using the FTP command PORT or PASV (depending on which mode you are running your client). So even though the primary port is PORT 21 &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s referred to as the COMMAND PORT. It&amp;rsquo;s not the PORT which is used to send/receive data. Which port will be used is randomly selected using the PORT/PASV command to minimize security issues. The way to fix this issue only seems to be to open a range of outgoing TCP ports above the 1000 range (what this range is &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;q=Ephemeral+Port+Range"&gt;still remains an issue&lt;/a&gt;) it seems to depend on the server &amp;ndash; and worst yet the server configuration. Most FTP servers will allow the emperical port range to change which might cause problems on our ISA server. In any case, the issue hasn&amp;rsquo;t been resolved yet &amp;ndash; but I will definietly post the solution once we find out.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Search for PGP key given a keyserver</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/search-for-pgp-key-given-a-keyserver/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2004 17:37:24 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/search-for-pgp-key-given-a-keyserver/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In Linux just do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;gpg --keyserver &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;#34;ldap://certserver.pgp.com&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; --search-keys &lt;span class="s2"&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;lt;e-mail address&amp;gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Note the option: &amp;ndash;keyserver can be other Keyservers like the &lt;a href="http://pgp.mit.edu/"&gt;MIT Key Server&lt;/a&gt; (pgp.mit.edu).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Random Numbers</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/random-numbers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2004 15:41:30 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/random-numbers/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are tons of masters, PhD thesis written on generating uniform (as in uniform distribution) random numbers using a computer. The problem with generating random numbers is finding a true source of entropy. The usual rand() or RND function found in most languages use the system clock as the source of entropy. This is perhaps the worst method of generating a random number; the reason being the change of entropy is predictable (because the change of time is predictable &amp;ndash; the millisecond counter changes 1/1000 sec). One technique (a technique used by PGP) uses other random sources from your computer. For instance mouse movements, thread counts or whatever else. The above techniques works wonders if you only want to generate small sets of random numbers. If you want to generate larger sets then you start to see recognizable patterns (this happens perhaps because you start of have predictable mouse movements, predictable thread counts and so on). I am working on a project that requires large sets of random numbers with low levels of predictability (note this level is not to be confused with the entropy value that is often paired with random numbers; what I am referring to here is the chi-square value). So as I was researching around the internet I came across this web-site: &lt;a href="http://www.random.org/"&gt;www.random.org&lt;/a&gt;. All they do is produce random numbers. The way the &lt;a href="http://www.random.org/"&gt;random.org&lt;/a&gt; random number generator works is quite simple. A radio is tuned into a frequency where nobody is broadcasting. The atmospheric noise picked up by the receiver is fed into a Sun SPARC workstation through the microphone port where it is sampled by a program as an eight bit mono signal at a frequency of 8KHz. The upper seven bits of each sample are discarded immediately and the remaining bits are gathered and turned into a stream of bits with a high content of entropy. Skew correction is performed on the bit stream, in order to ensure that there is an approximately even distribution of 0s and 1s. Recently they added a &lt;a href="http://www.random.org/soap.html"&gt;SOAP interface&lt;/a&gt; to their application; so what I will do is use their SOAP interface to receive some data and use that for my application. I will post the link to the resulting page as soon as I am done.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>