<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Home on Salman Quazi</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/</link><description>Recent content in Home on Salman Quazi</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 21:53:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.salmanq.com/en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Switched to Hugo from Wordpress</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/switched-to-hugo-from-wordpress/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 21:53:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/switched-to-hugo-from-wordpress/</guid><description>&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s been a relief to move away from the bloat of WordPress. I decided to use &lt;a href="https://gohugo.io">Hugo&lt;/a> and host all of the content in &lt;a href="https://github.com/splusq/splusq.github.io">Github&lt;/a>. I am even able to use &lt;a href="https://github.com/features/actions">Github Actions&lt;/a> to manage the continuous integration/delivery of the source to &lt;a href="https://pages.github.com">Github Pages&lt;/a> all entirely for free. While Github Pages, and Hugo both generate static html pages, I was able to enable comments, via &lt;a href="https://utteranc.es">utteranc.es&lt;/a> which stores the comments in Github as issues.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The overall experience is wonderful, clean and simple. The writing experience is also very enjoyable since markdown is a lot more predictable compared to WYSIWYG editors most WordPress authors rely on.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>5 things you probably didn't know about .NET WebSockets</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/5-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-net-websockets/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 23:45:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/5-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-net-websockets/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/04/websockets.png" alt="WebSockets"> As most of you probably already know WebSocket provides full-duplex communication over a single TCP connection. .NET 4.5 added support for WebSockets as part of the BCL. In this article I am going to talk about few of the subtleties that you need to think about.&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Connection upgrade is somewhat expensive&lt;/strong> WebSocket connections are initiated as traditional HTTP connections. The client then usually requests an &amp;ldquo;upgrade&amp;rdquo; to a WebSocket session, this upgrade process is relatively expensive. If you are interested in performance you may want to pool a set of connection that are already upgraded and use connections from the pool.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Building a service execution pipeline</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/building-a-service-execution-pipeline/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 05:19:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/building-a-service-execution-pipeline/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most software built today have a notion of a client and a service. This is even more true with mobile/web applications because you want your client apps to do as little as possible, and your service to do most of the heavy lifting. This allows you to improve your service without requiring constant client updates. Also since you have a single service that serves potentially various native clients (iOS, Android, or Windows Phone), being able to update it independently of your users gives you a clear competitive edge. So today I want to focus on building a service based on this notion of a &amp;ldquo;pipeline&amp;rdquo;. Most .NET client/service frameworks already have this concept. For instance, Windows Communication Foundation (WCF) has an execution pipeline, and so does ASP.NET. This allows you to extend the behavior of these frameworks at various points during the execution. But that&amp;rsquo;s not really what I want to talk about today. I want to talk about how &lt;em>you can build&lt;/em> your services such that you can add/remove functionality using a pipeline-style execution. As we are talking about the implementation of this pipeline I also want to take this opportunity to discuss good software design practices, and it&amp;rsquo;s uses. &lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/04/service-execution-pipeline.png" alt="service-execution-pipeline">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Self-Awareness</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/self-awareness/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2013 05:37:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/self-awareness/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sebastian_Junger">Sebastian Junger&lt;/a> (pronounced Younger) was on Bill Maher last night. Junger is an award winning Afghanistan war correspondent, and director, and his latest documentary &lt;a href="http://filmguide.sundance.org/film/13020/which_way_is_the_front_line_from_here_the_life_and_time_of_tim_hetherington">Which way is the front line from here?&lt;/a> has been proclaimed a success at the Sundance Film Festival this year. During the interview Bill asked why war felt like an addiction to some soldiers. In particular, what psychology drove this behavior? To that Sebastian responded: &amp;ldquo;The consequences in war are huge. The consequences even of small things. You don&amp;rsquo;t tie your shoe, you trip in a firefight, someone gets killed. And it gives you this strange almost Zen like focus on the details of life &amp;ndash; and everything starts to feel very meaningful, and friendships feel meaningful, everything has this kind of intensity. And soilders miss that sense of meaning and the bond that arises in that situation&amp;rdquo;. That&amp;rsquo;s a very insightful answer, and it&amp;rsquo;s probably why it stuck with me. No matter what I was doing I kept thinking about what he said, and how it applied to everything we do. His response wasn&amp;rsquo;t that soldiers do it for our country, or that they do it because they want to help humanity. While I am sure there&amp;rsquo;s a component of that, the reality is from an individual&amp;rsquo;s temporal perspective these grand reasons are too hard to see and therefore can&amp;rsquo;t be the reason for motivation. I think to a certain degree the same is true for most professionals - it&amp;rsquo;s arguable to compare a soldier to another profession but the general idea still applies. For instance, as software engineers, we build things that can change someone&amp;rsquo;s life, and we like to think that is the reason why we do what we do. But is it really? When we are trying to solve a hard technical problem at midnight, are we really doing it because it has an impact on someone&amp;rsquo;s life? Or is it something else? Self-awareness is key to happiness. If we know what it is that attracts us, we can certainly accentuate it or maybe even find other activities that lead to it. Without self-awareness the truth tends to hide behind social norms and hypes around you. The truth could hide even from yourself if you&amp;rsquo;re not careful. If you are lucky enough to love what you do, spend a day, take a walk and ask yourself: what it is that you really enjoy. Keep peeling away until there&amp;rsquo;s no more, and hopefully what you&amp;rsquo;re left with is your kernel of happiness.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introduction to Machine Learning</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/introduction-to-machine-learning-2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2013 07:39:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/introduction-to-machine-learning-2/</guid><description>&lt;p>In most computer science programs, machine learning is usually a graduate level course. It&amp;rsquo;s a specialization within the field of artificial intelligence, which is often thought of as a theoretical study than practical applications. But yet, machine learning today is used heavily to solve problems. Our team for instance, uses it to build acoustic models for speech recognition. It&amp;rsquo;s no longer a theory, it&amp;rsquo;s applied science. But if you wanted to start in this field, which I suspect is going to play a major role in software in the future, where do you start? I came across this free textbox from professor &lt;a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~welling/">Max Welling&lt;/a> for UCI Computer Science. His textbook &lt;a href="http://www.ics.uci.edu/~welling/teaching/273ASpring10/IntroMLBook.pdf">&amp;ldquo;A First Encounter with Machine Learning&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a> is available for free. While it&amp;rsquo;s not an entirely bedside reading, it is however written for engineers who are interested in learning about the various machine learning algorithms that are available today.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>.NET and Node.JS - Performance Comparison (Updated)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/net-and-node-js-performance-comparison/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 08:57:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/net-and-node-js-performance-comparison/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Update (3/31/2013 - 11:41 PM PST):&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This article has been updated! As most readers have commented the node.js async package is not asynchronous, which is what the original article was based on. I made an assumption I should not have. I have since rerun the tests taking this into account, as well as some of the changes recommended by &lt;a href="http://guillaume86.calepin.co/dotnet-vs-nodejs-performance.html">Guillaume Lecomte&lt;/a>. I have decided to update this existing post so that there&amp;rsquo;s no confusion in the future with the data. Thank you everyone for all the comments, posts and keeping me sane.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Improving Wordpress site speed on IIS</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/improving-wordpress-site-speed-on-iis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 19:03:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/improving-wordpress-site-speed-on-iis/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of the first things I did when I started this blog was to change the way static files are cached by IIS to improve site speed. Static files are things that aren&amp;rsquo;t going to change, things like CSS, JavaScript, images, documents, and so on. With IIS this is actually quite easy to achieve, you can start by making the following change to your web.config:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-xml" data-lang="xml">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;system.webServer&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;staticContent&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;clientCache&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">cacheControlMode=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;UseMaxAge&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">cacheControlMaxAge=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;7.00:00:00&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nt">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/staticContent&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/system.webServer&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>There&amp;rsquo;s a set of file extensions that&amp;rsquo;s already mapped to staticContent - so IIS only applies this change to all static contents. Also notice that we are caching the content on the client side. This means returning visitors will see a performance boost and we cache it for 7 days on the client side. If you have file extensions that are not part of the standard staticContent extension list, you can easily add it by doing:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ads</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ads/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2013 17:34:58 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ads/</guid><description>&lt;p>Came across this wonderful quote from &lt;a href="http://jeffhammerbacher.com/">Jeff Hammerbacher&lt;/a>: &amp;ldquo;The best minds of my generation are thinking about how to make people click ads&amp;rdquo;. I won&amp;rsquo;t get into the details of what the implications of this are - but I think you can figure it out.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Composition over Inheritance</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/composition-over-inheritance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 01:37:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/composition-over-inheritance/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are several ways to extend the behavior of a class. One of my preferred approach to extending behaviors is composition, and that is what we are going to talk about today. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a simple example of inheritance:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">class&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nc">Search&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">ISearch&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">IEnumerable&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">SearchResults&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Search&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Query&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">q&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">class&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nc">Related&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Search&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">IEnumerable&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RelatedEntities&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Related&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Query&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">q&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>So in this simple example, we extend Search and create Related - which provides some additional functionality. But a completely different approach which provides same results is to use composition:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Azure service monitoring</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/azure-service-monitoring/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2013 01:09:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/azure-service-monitoring/</guid><description>&lt;p>Monitoring your Azure services couldn&amp;rsquo;t get easier. Windows Azure recently released a capability to test connectivity of your service (REST or website) from over three continents. It&amp;rsquo;s super simple to setup. Login to your azure management console, add your website URL to monitor and select up to three locations to monitor from: &lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/03/azure-monitoring.png" alt="azure monitoring"> With that you can start getting response time, and uptime reports (my uptime was 100% so I didn&amp;rsquo;t show it here): &lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/03/azure-monreport.png" alt="azure website monitoring report"> In this case, Violet is Chicago, Blue is Hong Kong, and Green is Amsterdam.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>C-Sharp as a scripting language</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/c-sharp-as-a-scripting-language/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2013 04:49:07 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/c-sharp-as-a-scripting-language/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://scriptcs.net/">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/03/scriptcs-logo.png" alt="scriptcs.net logo">&lt;/a> Here&amp;rsquo;s a cool technology you might not have heard of: &lt;a href="http://scriptcs.net/">scriptcs&lt;/a>. Gives you the ability to use C# as a scripting language. It does this using the &lt;a href="http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/vstudio/roslyn.aspx">Rosyln compiler&lt;/a>. So here&amp;rsquo;s an example below, taken directly from the scriptcs website:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">System&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">System.IO&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">System.Web.Http&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">System.Web.Http.SelfHost&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">var&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">address&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;http://localhost:8080&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">var&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">conf&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">HttpSelfHostConfiguration&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Uri&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">address&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">));&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">conf&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Routes&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">MapHttpRoute&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;DefaultApi&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">routeTemplate&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;api/{controller}/{id}&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">defaults&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">id&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">RouteParameter&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Optional&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">var&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">server&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">HttpSelfHostServer&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">conf&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">server&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">OpenAsync&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">().&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Wait&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">();&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">Console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">WriteLine&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Listening...&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">Console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">ReadKey&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">();&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This is a simple way to startup a self-hosted server. But look at the various missing pieces here, no project file, no solution, no classes, no references (they happen through nugget packages) just a quick, frictionless, server. &lt;a href="http://codebetter.com/glennblock/2013/02/28/scriptcs-living-on-the-edge-in-c-without-a-project-on-the-wings-of-roslyn-and-nuget/">How elegant&lt;/a>. scriptcs was started by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/gblock">Glenn Block&lt;/a> (he contributed to WCF, MEF, node.js for Azure, among other things).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part III</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-iii/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 06:39:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-iii/</guid><description>&lt;p>We are at the finale of this three part series. &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/">In part I&lt;/a> we discussed the MVVM design pattern, &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/">in part II&lt;/a> we looked at the overall architecture and how the server side fits into the picture. In this article we are going to look at the client side of this and close with some final thoughts. The best place to start with the client is the HTML - so here&amp;rsquo;s the part of the HTML that&amp;rsquo;s interesting:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>IE Compatibility and W3C Validation</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ie-compatibility-and-w3c-validation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 08:17:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ie-compatibility-and-w3c-validation/</guid><description>&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a junkie when it comes to &lt;a href="http://validator.w3.org/check?uri=http%3A%2F%2Fsalmanq.com%2F&amp;amp;charset=%28detect+automatically%29&amp;amp;doctype=Inline&amp;amp;group=0&amp;amp;user-agent=W3C_Validator%2F1.3">markup validation&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s important to me that my sites are 100% XHTML/strict compatible. But recently I came across a situation that I thought I simply couldn&amp;rsquo;t get around. In this article I am going to show you how you can add the X-UA-Compatible attribute and at the same time validate your pages through W3C validation. My website had the following tag:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">meta&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">http-equiv&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;X-UA-Compatible&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">content&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;IE=edge,chrome=1&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This is a way to force IE to not display the compatibility mode button in the URL. Which I don&amp;rsquo;t want anyway. While the X-UA-Compatible is a standard meta key, the value IE=edge is not, and therefore the validator gave me an error. So I finally figured it out, I removed the tag from my template and added the meta tag to the standard HTTP header via web.config:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part II</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 04:23:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/">Last time we looked at what the MVVM pattern was&lt;/a>, and how it is used today in XAML-based applications. Today we are going to take a step further and build a mechanism to use the MVVM pattern on traditional web applications. Imagine how powerful it would be if your UI could evolve independently. We are going to build a simple web application that will display top 5 &amp;ldquo;memory intensive&amp;rdquo; processes on the server side, and here&amp;rsquo;s our basic architecture: &lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/03/mvvm-web-pattern.png" alt="MVVM Architecture for Web Applications">&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Microsoft on{x} - Automate your life</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/microsoft-onx-automate-your-life/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2013 19:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/microsoft-onx-automate-your-life/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.onx.ms/">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/03/microsoft-onx.png" alt="Microsoft on{x}">&lt;/a>&lt;a href="https://www.onx.ms/">Microsoft on{x}&lt;/a> is a set of services built by the team I work for. On{x} allows you to configure arbitrary actions during specific circumstances. For instance, on{x} provides an API called modeOfTransport. This API gives the developer the current mode of transportation - whether you are walking, running or driving. You can subscribe to a change in this event and build cool scenarios like when someone is going from driving to walking (imagine parking a car), your phone can automatically remember your parking location. On{x} also knows about your work location, your home, and other key areas of interest. So you can also trigger events, when you leave work, or arrive home and so on. The point however is that these are completely arbitrary, my team built the core set of services that enable these scenarios, and now it&amp;rsquo;s up to developers like you to leverage them to &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qfLMTsIJsoo">make the lives of others better&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How do you test your software?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/how-do-you-test-your-software/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 15:09:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/how-do-you-test-your-software/</guid><description>&lt;p>There seems to be two types of developers out there. One that believes in integration tests, and the other that believes in both unit and integration tests. Integration tests are tests that execute everything as if they were real &amp;ldquo;transactions&amp;rdquo; only to verify the expected results. For instance, if you were building a web application that managed a list of employees and their supervisors. Your integration test would probably add an employee to the database (actually add it), and then read it back from that database, and so on (from a test database of course). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong this, and in fact I would argue these types of tests are great. You need to write integration tests that exercise your entire stack. Without it would be like exercising without doing cardio. What differentiates a unit test from other types of tests is that you test a &amp;ldquo;unit&amp;rdquo; of your application alone. Now what that unit is, is up to you. But the point is you take a &lt;em>part&lt;/em> of your application and test it in &lt;em>isolation&lt;/em>. That part could be a class, it could be multiple sets of classes, but not your application as a whole - otherwise it would become an integration test. Seems like we have a conundrum here. We just argued that a integration test, tests everything, end-to-end, the entire stack &amp;ndash; and a unit test, tests a part of the application in isolation. Isn&amp;rsquo;t integration test then a superset of unit tests? And there is where the confusion lies. &lt;strong>So why write unit tests?&lt;/strong> While it is true that unit tests can often uncover bugs in the code, in reality unit tests actually help discover a far bigger problem; and that is design of your system. Unit tests can discover design issues if left unaddressed could severely impact your velocity to adapt to change. I would argue that if you can write proper tests for your system with good code coverage, then you have a well designed, cohesive system. Now unit testing alone is no silver bullet to design verification, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty close. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a really simple example:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part I</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 09:01:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/</guid><description>&lt;p>In this series I will be discussing how the MVVM pattern can be used for almost any type of web application. MVVM (a variant on the MVP pattern) - is a really powerful pattern that can be used in UI applications. Traditionally these UI applications has been WPF and Silverlight. In this article I will show you how you can use the same principles to build web applications. With MVVM you have the following three ideas:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Learning to program</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/learning-to-program/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 04:42:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/learning-to-program/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you or your kids want to learn how to program - you can start here: &lt;a href="http://www.code.org/">http://www.code.org/&lt;/a>. For instance, just &lt;a href="http://www.code.org/learn/khan-academy">see this example&lt;/a>. You have a great editor, where you can type and see results immediately on the right. On top of that, you have a video, with someone talking you through basic ideas like functions, and parameters. The site has support from top names like &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=nKIu9yen5nc">Bill Gates and Mark Zuckerberg&lt;/a>. And if all this wasn&amp;rsquo;t enough - just think for a second by 2020, there will be 1,000,000 (that&amp;rsquo;s a million) &lt;a href="http://techcrunch.com/2013/01/22/code-org-launches-to-help-make-computer-programming-accessible-to-everyone/">more jobs than there will be students&lt;/a> who know how to code. Not that you&amp;rsquo;d want to learn something just because there&amp;rsquo;s a job out there. But the numbers show the scale of the problem we are heading towards.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Asynchronous Anonymous Methods</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/asynchronous-anonymous-methods/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Feb 2013 04:04:42 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/asynchronous-anonymous-methods/</guid><description>&lt;p>So a cool new feature in .NET 4.5 is the ability to create anonymous methods that are asynchronous (async).&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Task&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Run&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kd">async&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&amp;gt;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">await&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Task&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Yield&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">());&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s just a cool way of saying do nothing!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Task Timeouts</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/task-timeouts/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Feb 2013 03:25:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/task-timeouts/</guid><description>&lt;p>When dealing with .NET tasks – we often want to timeout the operation if it does not complete within a certain period of time. For instance, if you make an asynchronous WebRequest call – you may want to timeout this asynchronous operation within 3 seconds if you don’t get a response back. In the past, we had to create Timers to monitor the Task (or the Thread) for completion in the callback of the timer, and then do other crazy gymnastics to make it all play well together. However, the result was a code that was extremely difficult to understand because you had these disparate methods, without any cohesiveness within the code. With .NET 4.5 we can simplify this dramatically.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Brief introduction to PRISM</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/brief-introduction-to-prism/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2011 14:55:10 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/brief-introduction-to-prism/</guid><description>&lt;p>Before I go into the technical details of this article. I want to provide some context for this discussion. So we are using &lt;a href="http://compositewpf.codeplex.com/">PRISM&lt;/a> to develop a user-interface (UI) platform in the context of a Silverlight (but they apply to WPF also). The idea behind the UI platform is we will provide the basic functional look and feel and various plumbing (such as security, service encapsulation, messaging and exception handling, among others) and allow others to develop modules/components on top. PRISM allows us to do this quite well. Let’s assume for a second, you have a system where a user can initiate an order, and then track the shipment status of that order. PRISM allows us to separate the concerns of this applications into two distinct tasks. (1) ordering, and (2) shipment tracking (and perhaps even further, but let’s keep it simple). Each of these could be developed as separate modules, and therefore separate DLLs, and possibly by separate teams. In the end, with PRISM, we can &lt;strong>&lt;em>dynamically compose&lt;/em>&lt;/strong> these at runtime even though they are independent components. So if you can imagine for a second, all the base functionality that we talked earlier is hosted in a component itself usually referred to as the Shell. The Shell is like the hosting application, where everything comes together. If there’s any resemblance to web applications, as Masterpage is to a ASP.NET page, a Shell is to a Silverlight/WPF application. That’s one way to look at it. So that’s the general overview for our discussion. And you can get a lot of good content about PRISM from Karl Shifflett, John Papa. With PRISM (and also few other technologies like MEF) what we are able to do is we are able to surface modules on the fly based on a modules catalog (one of many ways). One key architectural decision we made early on was that the Shell would be independent of the modules – meaning the Shell does not have any strong references to the modules. This allows us to introduce new modules without actually recompiling the Shell. But many examples out there do exactly that, they either (1) add strong references to Modules from the Shell or (2) they use something known as a ModulesCatalog file. Which is a XAML file that weakly defines the modules list. But again, the ModulesCatalog.xaml file is backed into the Shell – and therefore part of the XAP. That brings us back to the some of the same restrictions. Part of the problem we have is we have several teams, teams that are out of control, developing modules. &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to check if Integrated Windows Authentication is available?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/how-to-check-if-integrated-windows-authentication-is-available/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 13:13:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/how-to-check-if-integrated-windows-authentication-is-available/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked on an intranet site, you often want to know, programmatically, if a client that&amp;rsquo;s accessing your website has the ability to automatically login to your site (Integrated Windows Authentication). With Integration Windows Authentication, Windows can basically send (as a HTTP header) the currently &amp;ldquo;logged on&amp;rdquo; username. So your application can access this LOGON_USER HTTP header and go from there. I won&amp;rsquo;t get into the details of how to setup integrated windows authentication, but basically the idea is you go into IIS and for a given resource (a folder or a file) on your site you change the directory security to Integrated Windows Authentication. Once this is done, when a client visits your local site (the definition of local depends on the gateway or group policy), IE switches to the &amp;ldquo;intranet site&amp;rdquo; profile which allows the automatic authentication. That&amp;rsquo;s the broad picture. But unfortunately, if the same users visits that same website from another location, say from their home, they will end up getting the ugly NTLM authentication box - and most of the times they don&amp;rsquo;t know what to do. Partly because their experience has changed, at work they were simply &amp;ldquo;logged in&amp;rdquo; without doing anything and now they have to login and often times need to prefix their username with domain username format. That&amp;rsquo;s not good. So it&amp;rsquo;s useful to be able to find out programmatically if integrated windows authentication is available, if it is then you simply login using the integration authentication, otherwise you provide the user with a clean and simple forms authentication system. So let&amp;rsquo;s start with some JavaScript code:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Better Presentations</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/better-presentations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2011 13:19:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/better-presentations/</guid><description>&lt;p>You can drastically improve your PowerPoint presentations by simply leveraging &lt;a href="http://www.officelabs.com/projects/pptPlex/Pages/default.aspx">&lt;strong>pptPlex&lt;/strong>&lt;/a>!  It’s a add-on for PowerPoint to build dynamic, contextual presentations. Contextual presentations allows your viewers to see the global context of your discussion, which in turn helps them to follow your line of thought. &lt;a href="http://www.officelabs.com/projects/pptPlex/Pages/default.aspx">Watch some of the videos on the pptPlex website&lt;/a> to see what’s possible.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Rendering Step 1 of … (ASP.NET)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/rendering-step-1-of-asp-net/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2007 01:01:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/rendering-step-1-of-asp-net/</guid><description>&lt;p>The MultiView control, Wizard control or even a custom panel-based control is very useful to collect large sets of data in wizard form; and it&amp;rsquo;s often useful to give visual ques to the user as to which step he/she is in. Something similar to:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/09/screenshot.jpg" title="StepMaker-Screenshot">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/09/screenshot.jpg" alt="StepMaker-Screenshot">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The following ASP.NET code/C# allows us to build a dynamic step control which grows or shrinks automatically given the number of views you have in a MultiView control, or the number of steps in a wizard control.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Presentation on jQuery</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/presentation-on-jquery/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2007 02:32:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/presentation-on-jquery/</guid><description>&lt;p>I presented a topic on jQuery at our campus web publishers meeting. Here are the &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/06/cwp.zip" title="jQuery presentation (CWP)">sample pages and the PowerPoint presentation&lt;/a>. I will talk more discussions on jQuery and how it has helped us to build a powerful web-application next week.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Automatic Documentation</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/automatic-documentation/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2007 19:16:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/automatic-documentation/</guid><description>&lt;p>Generally all programmers are lazy&amp;ndash;and specially when it comes to documentation because it takes so much time and doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily produce any material benefit. &lt;a href="http://www.roland-weigelt.de/ghostdoc/">GhostDoc&lt;/a>1, designed by Roland Weigelt, is a plugin for Visual Studio 2005 that automates the generation of XML comments. For example if you have the following C#1 function:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">User&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">GetByUserName&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">string&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">userName&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>GhostDoc will automatically generate:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="cs">/// &amp;lt;summary&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cs">/// Gets the name of the by user.&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cs">/// &amp;lt;/summary&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cs">/// &amp;lt;param name=&amp;#34;userName&amp;#34;&amp;gt;Name of the user.&amp;lt;/param&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cs">/// &amp;lt;returns&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/returns&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">User&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">GetByUserName&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">string&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">userName&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>That&amp;rsquo;s pretty amazing. Notice how GhostDoc recognizes Camel and Pascal case variables names. And best of all once the basic structure of the comment is prepared it&amp;rsquo;s actually not very difficult to type in few words that essentially sums up what the function does if GhostDoc hasn&amp;rsquo;t already done it. Finally, since GhostDoc integrates directly with Visual Studio all you have to do is right click the function signature and click on: &amp;ldquo;Document this&amp;rdquo; and done! GhostDoc also supports: enums, getters and setters, inheritance, interfaces and so on&amp;hellip; [1] &lt;a href="http://www.roland-weigelt.de/ghostdoc/">GhostDoc&lt;/a> currently only supports C#&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using SSIS to Access Network Resources</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-ssis-to-access-network-resources/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2007 01:38:29 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-ssis-to-access-network-resources/</guid><description>&lt;p>SSIS (SQL Server Integration Services) is the replacement for DTS in SQL 2005. One of the more deceitful concepts in SSIS is it&amp;rsquo;s security context. When you run a SSIS package form your Visual Studio Environment, it obviously runs under a different security context (most possibly as you&amp;ndash;the developer) than it would run if it was run as a scheduled service on the SQL server itself. So let&amp;rsquo;s say you&amp;rsquo;ve developed a SSIS package that uses resources within your domain, such as accessing a network drive. How will SSIS access such a resource? As you may know, SSIS packages are executed by the SQL server agent, which by default uses the native [NT AUTHORITY\SYSTEM] account1 to execute your packages. Since this is a local account you cannot use it when you need access to resources external to the SQL server box. In order to access domain level resources, you need to use a domain proxy. A domain proxy allows the SQL agent to proxy on an existing domain account when it executes a package. The first step is to create a credential. Connect to your SQL server, expand security, right click credentials and new credential. Fill-in the dialog box to something like this: &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/domainproxy1.jpg" title="SQL 2005 - Credentials">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/domainproxy1.thumbnail.jpg" alt="SQL 2005 - Credentials">&lt;/a> The second step is to create a domain proxy, expand SQL Server Agent, right click proxies and click new proxy. Fill in the dialog box something similar to the image shown on the left. Identity is the domain account you are going to use and the password to the domain account.&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/domainproxy2.jpg" title="SQL 2005 - Proxy Accounts">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/domainproxy2.thumbnail.jpg" alt="SQL 2005 - Proxy Accounts">&lt;/a> Once this is done, expand SQL Server Agent, right click Proxies and click on New Proxy. The resulting dialog box should look something like the image on the left. For the credential name use the credential you just made.&lt;br>
&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/domainproxy3.jpg" title="SQL 2005 - SSIS Run As">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/domainproxy3.thumbnail.jpg" alt="SQL 2005 - SSIS Run As">&lt;/a> Now the last step is to modify the SSIS package to use this proxy account. So right click Jobs under SQL Server Agent, right click the job that you want to run using this proxy account, click properties, go to the steps tab, click on edit at the bottom of the screen. Change Run As to the new proxy account you just created. The resulting dialog box should look something like the image on the left. Make sure the domain account, which you are using during the step when you created the credential, has access to all the network resources this package needs access to. [1] SQL Agent actually does not use the system account but runs in the context of the SQLAgentUser group on the local machine, the [NT AUTHORITY\SYSTEM] account is by default part of the SQLAgentUser group.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Script Task reading/returning data</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/script-task-readingreturning-data/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 May 2007 23:58:45 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/script-task-readingreturning-data/</guid><description>&lt;p>When you are using the Script Task in SSIS it&amp;rsquo;s often useful to have the script task return data, and also at times useful to have access to external data. Once you drop a Script Task onto the designer and go to it&amp;rsquo;s editor, under the script tab you&amp;rsquo;ll find two attributes: ReadOnlyVariables, ReadWriteVariables. The first allows the script to access external &lt;strong>user variables&lt;/strong> for reading, while the latter allows write access. It&amp;rsquo;s important to realize that we are talking about user variables which is usually under the &lt;em>User::&lt;/em> namespace. So every variable you list must be prefixed by: User::. If you don&amp;rsquo;t the script assumes System::. So here&amp;rsquo;s a screen shot of what a script task might look like: &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/script-task1.jpg" title="Script Task (Variables)">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/05/script-task1.thumbnail.jpg" alt="Script Task (Variables)">&lt;/a> Once you click on the design script you get an editor where you are allowed to type VB.NET code. At this point SSIS script tasks do not support C#. Here&amp;rsquo;s a sample of how you can access a user variable and set a value to it. As you can see from the sample code below, SSIS variables are not typed:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reverse a linked list recursively</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/reverse-a-linked-list-recursively/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2007 23:26:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/reverse-a-linked-list-recursively/</guid><description>&lt;p>A question came up the other day while I was helping a friend of mine about recursively reversing a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Linked_list">singly linked list&lt;/a>. The moment I heard about it I came up with a solution, but turns out the solution requires the function to accept the following signature:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-c" data-lang="c">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">*&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nf">reverseList&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">*&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">l&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This actually poses a problem because there&amp;rsquo;s no way to keep track of the head, or maintain any back pointers which could&amp;rsquo;ve been done if the function accepted a second parameter. Anyway, so I thought about it and initially started with some of the base cases:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Legacy code</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/legacy-code/</link><pubDate>Thu, 17 May 2007 00:52:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/legacy-code/</guid><description>&lt;p>I manage a good portion of legacy code, written by so called consultants, and I can&amp;rsquo;t believe how many places I have seen code like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">bool&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">flag&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">if&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">x&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">==&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">y&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">flag&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">else&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">flag&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kc">false&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Or a variation of this&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">bool&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">flag&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kc">false&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">if&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">x&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">==&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">y&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nx">flag&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kc">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Although the latter is better, you can write an equivalent statement as follows:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">bool&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">flag&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">x&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">==&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nx">y&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>How much easier is that to read? In my opinion a lot! I&amp;rsquo;ve seen arguments against that however, suggesting that it&amp;rsquo;s hard to read and not &amp;ldquo;extensible&amp;rdquo;. Meaning, if your if clause contains more than one action then my proposed statement wouldn&amp;rsquo;t work and would need to be rewritten. First of all, how&amp;rsquo;s that not readable? In fact, I feel it&amp;rsquo;s more readable than the other statements mainly because in a single line you see that flag is true if x equals y.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using Control Adapters</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-control-adapters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2007 04:55:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-control-adapters/</guid><description>&lt;p>ASP.NET 2.0 introduced a new way of modifying how ASP.NET renders a control. For example, when you say:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">asp:textbox&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">id&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;FirstName&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">runat&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;server&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>You have very limited control over how the control actually renders. You can specify a &lt;em>cssclass&lt;/em> to modify the look and feel, but the actual HTML rendering is limited to what&amp;rsquo;s available from the ASP.NET server attributes. For example you cannot add client-side onfocus or onblur statements. This is where Control Adapters comes in. Control adapters allows you to modify the rendering of any server control, with complete freedom.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Automatic Printing</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/automatic-printing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2005 23:42:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/automatic-printing/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Summary:&lt;/strong> Learn about automatic printing in a Windows platform using WScript.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Automatic printing is a subject you will find a lot of content about on the internet &amp;ndash; but most of it is useless. It&amp;rsquo;s a massive collection of try-this-try-that. I was searching for some descent content on how to do scheduled automatic printing but spent far more time that I would like to. Finally I arrive at this code:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Four Part Naming Convention in SQL Server</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/four-part-naming-convention-in-sql-server/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2005 05:41:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/four-part-naming-convention-in-sql-server/</guid><description>&lt;p>In SQL server if you want to reference a table using four-part naming convention and you receive the error message: &lt;strong>Server &amp;lsquo;xxxx&amp;rsquo; is not configured for DATA ACCESS&lt;/strong>. Then you need to execute this statement against the target server:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-sql" data-lang="sql">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">EXEC&lt;/span>&lt;span class="w"> &lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">sp_serveroption&lt;/span>&lt;span class="w"> &lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;xxxx&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;DATA ACCESS&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">TRUE&lt;/span>&lt;span class="w">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>&amp;hellip; that should fix the problem. An obvious point here is to replace xxxx with the target server.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CTRL+ALT+DEL Twice?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ctrlaltdel-twice/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2005 04:21:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ctrlaltdel-twice/</guid><description>&lt;p>In Windows XP pressing CTRL+ALT+DEL twice in the login screen will take you to the classic login screen where you can manually type in the username and password to authenticate yourself. &lt;a href="http://blogs.msdn.com/oldnewthing/archive/2005/09/14/466051.aspx">According to a Microsoft employee&lt;/a> this feature maybe removed in future releases of Windows or worst yet it might be removed in future service packs. This would have caused serious problems for me because non-of the users I have on the intial list are administrators to the system. That means without that feature I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t have been able to login to the computer as an administrator (&lt;em>unless I did run-as on computer management MMC and made myself administrator and then loged as me again&lt;/em>). But just a note that whoever is depending on this should be aware!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using ASP.NET to authenticate against AD</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-asp-net-to-authenticate-against-ad/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Sep 2005 02:58:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-asp-net-to-authenticate-against-ad/</guid><description>&lt;p>The company I work for reliies heavily on active-directory to organize, authenticate and integrate. In order to login to the intranet from our site, we currently request the integrated windows authentication box and ask the user to login. For some people this was a little flattering because it didn&amp;rsquo;t really say why the login was taking place &amp;ndash; where are they loging into and so on. So to remedy this issue, I am working on a ASP.NET product that will authenticate against AD. This can be done using DirectoryServices provided within the .NET framework.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Finding Content in your files</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/finding-content-in-your-files/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Sep 2005 00:57:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/finding-content-in-your-files/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you want to search text files in your computer for a specific string you can do this easily using the following code:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">for&lt;/span> /f &lt;span class="s2">&amp;#34;tokens=*&amp;#34;&lt;/span> %i IN &lt;span class="o">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s1">&amp;#39;dir /s /b *.asp&amp;#39;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">)&lt;/span> DO find /I &lt;span class="s2">&amp;#34;depthomepages&amp;#34;&lt;/span> %i &amp;gt;&amp;gt; output.txt
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>You can replace dir /s /b *.asp to something more appropriate. You can alternatively search only specific folders also, by simply modifying the dir arguments.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Recursion in SQL</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/recursion-in-sql/</link><pubDate>Sun, 11 Sep 2005 15:21:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/recursion-in-sql/</guid><description>&lt;p>Oracle database supports a very strange construct called: start with, and connect by. For instance if you have a table which has two columns one that defines the parent of the other column such as:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> Parent Child
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="m">0&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">1&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="m">1&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">9&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="m">9&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">7&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="m">7&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">2&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The parent of 2 is 7 and 7&amp;rsquo;s parent is nine and 9&amp;rsquo;s parent is one and so on until finally 1 who parent is 0 signifying no parent. To find the root or the top-level parent given an ID cannot be done easily without recursion and SQL server does not support recursion in SQL contructs. But Oracle does, here&amp;rsquo;s how we can solve this problem in Oracle:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typed ToArray() from ArrayList</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/typed-toarray-from-arraylist/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2005 07:47:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/typed-toarray-from-arraylist/</guid><description>&lt;p>To get a typed Array of type int [] from an ArrayList you can do the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">[])&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">TestArray&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">ToArray&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">typeof&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">));&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>First the ToArray() function accepts a System.Type argument which is what it uses to convert the Array to type int. However, the return type of ToArray() is still object so we will need to cast that as well which can be done using the (int []).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>FTP &amp; Microsoft ISA Server 2004</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ftp-microsoft-isa-server-2004/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2005 13:31:57 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/ftp-microsoft-isa-server-2004/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/isaserver/default.mspx">Microsoft ISA (Internet Security and Acceleration Server) 2004&lt;/a> is a tool to secure and accelerate (as the name suggests) networks running on Windows platforms. It&amp;rsquo;s a very powerful tool and is one of the most flexible firewalls I have seen in the market. Where I work, Microsoft ISA actually replaced several CISCO firewalls. Not only were we able to migrate all the access lists rules we were able to do far more than that. Just so we a sense of our setup we have two Microsoft ISA servers running. One that handles the X subnet and the handles the Y subnet. All of the servers and static-IP workstations are hosted on the Y subnet. The ISA server that firewalls the Y subnet allows more incoming and outgoing ports to facilitate testing, production level data transfer and so on. Me and our system administrators spent almost all day today trying to figure out a solution to a strange problem. When we FTP from the Y subnet (the static subnet) to a external box, we can successfully login because PORT 21 is port. However, after logging in we cannot upload any files. After some researching I found out that FTP does not receive data from PORT 21 but changes the incoming port dynamically which is set using the FTP command PORT or PASV (depending on which mode you are running your client). So even though the primary port is PORT 21 &amp;ndash; it&amp;rsquo;s referred to as the COMMAND PORT. It&amp;rsquo;s not the PORT which is used to send/receive data. Which port will be used is randomly selected using the PORT/PASV command to minimize security issues. The way to fix this issue only seems to be to open a range of outgoing TCP ports above the 1000 range (what this range is &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;q=Ephemeral+Port+Range">still remains an issue&lt;/a>) it seems to depend on the server &amp;ndash; and worst yet the server configuration. Most FTP servers will allow the emperical port range to change which might cause problems on our ISA server. In any case, the issue hasn&amp;rsquo;t been resolved yet &amp;ndash; but I will definietly post the solution once we find out.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Recursive Fun (C#)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/recursive-fun-c/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2005 02:17:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/recursive-fun-c/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recursive functions can be a lot of fun! I was playing around with a collegue of mine at work about solving recursive problems. And we both worked on a problem of deciding weather a number is the median in a list of numbers. Here&amp;rsquo;s my solution:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">System&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">class&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nc">MedianRecursive&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">private&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">delegate&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">bool&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Function&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">A&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">B&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">private&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kd">static&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">bool&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">GreaterThan&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">A&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">B&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">A&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">B&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">private&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kd">static&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">bool&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">LessThan&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">A&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">B&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">A&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">b&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">private&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kd">static&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">string&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Partition&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[]&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">M&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Position&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Function&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Compare&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">if&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Position&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Length&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">else&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">((&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Compare&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Position&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">],&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">M&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">))?&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Position&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">].&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">ToString&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">():&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Partition&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">M&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Position&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">1&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Compare&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">private&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kd">static&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">bool&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Median&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[]&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">M&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">return&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Partition&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">M&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">0&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Function&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">GreaterThan&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)).&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Length&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">==&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Partition&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">List&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">M&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">0&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Function&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LessThan&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)).&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Length&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kd">static&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">void&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Main&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">string&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">[]&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">args&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">){&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">WriteLine&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Is Median: {0}&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Median&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">[]{&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">1&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">2&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">3&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">4&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">5&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">6&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">7&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">},&lt;/span> &lt;span class="m">4&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)?&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Yes&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">:&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;No&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">));&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The most obvious way of solving this problem is to sort the list of numbers, go the middle of the sorted list and check to see weather List[Middle] == M. However, that&amp;rsquo;s a little overkill. Why sort when all we need to do is check if a number a list&amp;rsquo;s median? The method I used partitioned the list into two subsets. The first subset contains all numbers less than M and the second subset contains all numbers greater than M. If M is the median of the list then the first subset&amp;rsquo;s length should equal the second subsets length. SIMPLE!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Partial Classes</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/partial-classes/</link><pubDate>Fri, 24 Jun 2005 23:48:19 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/partial-classes/</guid><description>&lt;p>Out of several enchancements available in .NET 2.0 &lt;strong>partial classes&lt;/strong> is one of them. Partial classes simply means that you can break your class and write them separately (as if they were separate entities). This becomes a useful feature when you have a large class that does more than one thing. If you open a software engineering book, you are likely to find statements like: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;your function/classes should do one thing and do it well&amp;rdquo;. Yes, this is an ideal situation but often times when modeling the real-world the developer is forced to combine multiple funcationlity within one class. This is specially true in a web-environment because there is a tendency to combine UI and logic. &lt;strong>Pros&lt;/strong> The .NET model simply does an amazing job of separating design and logic. But with the current model, if you add some controls your classes will contain a list of all the WebControl members such as TextBox, RadioButton and so on. This is really UI and should be separate from the logic of the class. In .NET 2.0 however, you can separate all the UI members and move it to a partial class. Then write another partial class that will contain only the logic side of the page. A far more clearner and easier to maintain technique. &lt;strong>Cons&lt;/strong> Since partial classes allow you to separate the class definitions anywhere within the current namespace, there might be a tendency from the developer to have large partial classes that does far too many things. What this does is you have a structured program masked with OOP keywords all over the place, and not a &amp;ldquo;true&amp;rdquo; object-oriented program. To the programmer it might appear as if he/she is using sound software-engineering methodologies because they are using class, structures, delegates and partial classes! Underneath all this keywords however is a flat structured program with lots of functions! So in conclusion, even though partial classes a great way to separate &amp;ldquo;functionality&amp;rdquo; of a class one must be careful and continue to follow sound practices.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>XMLHttp</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/xmlhttp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2005 02:11:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/xmlhttp/</guid><description>&lt;p>XMLHttp is the future of web application development. It allows threaded communication between the client and the server without ever leaving the page. If more advanced JavaScript features are standardized this might mean that a web application will act and feel very much like a regular windows application. Up until now, one of the major differences between a windows application and a web application was statelessness. However, with XMLHttp this is reduced much further because a state will no longer be round-trip from the server, it will be when the user enters a page does several thousand things and leaves the page (when they leave the page the state is lost) however during those thousand events all the state will be maintainted &amp;ndash; this can be done using XMLHttp. &lt;strong>So what is XMLHttp exactly?&lt;/strong> XMLHttp allows XML formatted (ideally) data to be passed to a server-side page using client side script. The response from that input can then be read back using a client side script and some actions performed based on that output. Consider this scenario, let&amp;rsquo;s say you are writing a address verification system. Your boss thinks that the user shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to pick the state because just typing in the zip code should automatically select the appropriate state. In the olden days in order to do this you would have to do a Postback on the server and check the zipcode against your database to resolve the state. With XMLHttp once the user types in the zipcode the zipcode is passed to the server to resolve the state. When the result is found the dropdown box for the state is changed to the appropriate state &amp;ndash; without ever leaving the page. Next time I will post some sample XMLHttp code and discuss this further.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The trailing slash</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/the-trailing-slash/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2005 00:47:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/the-trailing-slash/</guid><description>&lt;p>Sometimes a simple change as adding a slash may improve the performance of your web-applications. Consider this: the link &lt;a href="http://www.salmanq.com">www.salmanq.com&lt;/a> is slower than &lt;a href="http://www.salmanq.com/">www.salmanq.com/&lt;/a> (the only difference being the trailing slash). They will both work but the latter is faster. When this link: &lt;a href="https://www.onupol.com">www.onupol.com&lt;/a> is followed the web-server returns a 301 (Moved Permanently) pointing to &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/">www.salmanq.com/&lt;/a> that&amp;rsquo;s one extra round trip to and from the server per link. If you have a site that&amp;rsquo;s running without the trailing slash and you have 10K+ visitors you will certainly start to feel the consequence.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Old bugs are harder to catch</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/old-bugs-are-harder-to-catch/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2005 03:18:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/old-bugs-are-harder-to-catch/</guid><description>&lt;p>About three years ago I worked on an application that in-part had to blend in with several other applications. Among many features one of them was to automatically generate something known as deadlines. The actual details are far to complicated to explain in details here, so I will use a simpler example.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Assume that you have four types of documents each have their own specific way of computing deadline. One of them follows a rule like:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>MySQL version information</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/mysql-version-information/</link><pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2005 07:32:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/mysql-version-information/</guid><description>&lt;p>You can use this simple command to find the MySQL version you are running:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-sql" data-lang="sql">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="w"> &lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">Version&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span>&lt;span class="w"> &lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">as&lt;/span>&lt;span class="w"> &lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">Version&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="w">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Hope that helps.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>ValueType Boxing</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/valuetype-boxing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2005 00:49:21 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/valuetype-boxing/</guid><description>&lt;p>In .NET an interesting phehomenon occurs known as &amp;ldquo;boxing&amp;rdquo;. Let me illustrate the problem and then we will look at the possible solutions:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">System&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">using&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nn">System.Collections&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">class&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nc">Test&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">struct&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nc">BankAccount&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cm">/* A simple BankAccount structure */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">float&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Balance&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cm">/* Balance in the account */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">BankAccount&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">float&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">_Balance&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cm">/* overloaded-contructor */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Balance&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">_Balance&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="cm">/* A method to charge the account */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">void&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">ChargeAccount&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">float&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Fee&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Balance&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">-=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Fee&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="kd">public&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kd">static&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">void&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Main&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">ArrayList&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Accounts&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">ArrayList&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">();&lt;/span> &lt;span class="cm">/* An array */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Accounts&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Add&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">BankAccount&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">100&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">));&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Accounts&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Add&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">BankAccount&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">200&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">));&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Accounts&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Add&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="k">new&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">BankAccount&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">300&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">));&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="cm">/* Line: 21 */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="cm">/* Go through each account and ChargeAccount 5.0 */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">foreach&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">BankAccount&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Account&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">in&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Accounts&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Account&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">ChargeAccount&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">((&lt;/span>&lt;span class="kt">float&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>&lt;span class="m">5.0&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">WriteLine&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Boxed: &amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Account&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Balance&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="cm">/* Go through each account and print the balance */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">foreach&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">BankAccount&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Account&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">in&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Accounts&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">Console&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">WriteLine&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Un-boxed: &amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">Account&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">.&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">Balance&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The program outputs the following:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Uncertaintly Principal and Software Engineering</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/uncertaintly-principal-and-software-engineering/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2005 23:06:14 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/uncertaintly-principal-and-software-engineering/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://scienceworld.wolfram.com/physics/UncertaintyPrinciple.html">Uncertainty Principal&lt;/a> is a principle of quantum mechanics postulated by &lt;a href="http://nobelprize.org/physics/laureates/1932/">Nobel laureate&lt;/a> &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Werner_Heisenberg">Werner Heisenberg&lt;/a> in the 1920s which states that it is not possible to determine both the position and the momentum of a particle at the same instant. The reason he argued, was that the act of &amp;ldquo;observing&amp;rdquo; the particle changes its behavior with respect to what is being measured. He was one of the first scientists to bring in probability into the predictable science of physics.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Form posts and CacheControl</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/form-posts-and-cachecontrol/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2005 23:56:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/form-posts-and-cachecontrol/</guid><description>&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have an HTML form which posts to another page, and that page in turn posts to other page(s) (maybe even to itself). Consider what happens in a very common scenario such as this:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>User visits page 1&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Types in username and password&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Posts to page 2 (valid user)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>User sorts a column in page 2 which posts the column name and the order to page 2.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Page 2 reloads.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Now if the user pushes the back button when he/she is step 5 he/she will see one of two things: (1) Either the previous page will load (which is the behavior we would like to have) OR (2) the infamous &amp;ldquo;Warning: Page has Expired&amp;rdquo; message will appear in the screen.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Option Groups</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/option-groups/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2005 01:50:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/option-groups/</guid><description>&lt;p>Not many people know about this. In a HTML dropdown (select) there is a option group tag that groups your options together. For instance:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">select&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;cars&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">optgroup&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">label&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Honda&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>Honda Accord DX&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>Honda Accord LX&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>Honda Accord EX&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">optgroup&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">optgroup&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">label&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;BMW&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>BMW 530iL&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>BMW 640iL&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>BMW 740i&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">option&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">optgroup&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>If you &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/optiongroup.php">run the code above&lt;/a> you will &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/optiongroup.php">notice&lt;/a> users can&amp;rsquo;t even select the option group (which is perfectly valid). And the automatic indendation within the sub-groups is very useful also. This feature is supported by Opera and IE browsers. The actual version details you will have to find out.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why run as doesn’t work on explorer.exe?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/why-run-as-doesnt-work-on-explorer-exe/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2005 20:54:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/why-run-as-doesnt-work-on-explorer-exe/</guid><description>&lt;p>You will notice in windows no matter how you want to &amp;ldquo;Run as&amp;rdquo; explorer.exe it will not work. Almost all programs you can right-click or hold CTRL and right click to get the run as option but with explorer this doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem work. You cannot even use the command line tool runas /u:administrator to run explorer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Explorer.exe is a special task. It actually runs all the time and is responsible for the taskbar and other features on the Windows desktop, press CTRL+ALT+DEL right now and you will see explorer.exe is running, you can also kill the process (don&amp;rsquo;t do it if you have important things going, but for the sake of experiment you can try) and you will notice your taskbar and your desktop will clear away. You can once again run the process by clicking File-&amp;gt;New Task-&amp;gt;explorer.exe&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Can UIs produce bugs?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/can-uis-produce-bugs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2005 18:10:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/can-uis-produce-bugs/</guid><description>&lt;p>All developers are aware how programming errors such as logic error, exception error or incorrect input data can produce bugs. But can UIs produce bugs or at least attract the user towards a bug? The answer yes! And these bugs tend to be quite difficult to catch because each user react to the UI in a different way. And the fact that programmers are so used to the behaviors of the default controls in a GUI environment it&amp;rsquo;s hard for them to test the application for UI confusions. Unfortunately this is more true in a web platform than in it is in a let&amp;rsquo;s say windows application. In a windows application the developer has more control and therefore can enforce a UI path whereas in a web-application the user is partially in control. Consider what happens in Gmail for instance, if you write an e-mail and half way through you close the browser by mistake what happens? Gmail will not give you any alerts instead the browser will close and you will have lost everything you typed (assuming you didn&amp;rsquo;t save a draft). Now let&amp;rsquo;s follow through the same steps but this time on a Windows application. Open up outlook and create a new message, now no matter how you want to close the window weather it&amp;rsquo;s closing the &amp;ldquo;New message&amp;rdquo; window or Outlook itself completely you will have to confirm that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to save the message and still quit. Now of course the example I am presenting above is obvious enough that no one makes this mistake. Everyone knows that if you are using Hotmail, Yahoo Mail or Gmail you should save your message first before quitting. But in a complex application (specially when the user is not used to it) this UI problem can get quite scary. This issue came into my attention when I released a fairly large application into production and some of the users were having trouble submiting information to us through the app. After some investigation I realized that it was the UI that was confusing some users. To make long stories short, in a web environment we as programmers must be cautious as to how to design our UIs because we have several boundaries that we have to work against, the lack of control when it comes to UI in a web environment, the statelessness of web-applications and the constant client-server connection all play a role into introducing strange bugs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Optimizing Regular Expressions</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/optimizing-regular-expressions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2005 16:23:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/optimizing-regular-expressions/</guid><description>&lt;p>Optimizing regular expressions is an exceptionally complex field. A vast majority of the problems within this field is &lt;code>NP&lt;/code> or &lt;code>NP-COMPLETE&lt;/code>. Meaning that their solutions cannot be bound (time/space) under any definite polynomial.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All APIs (such as: .NET, PHP, ASP (classic VB really), JavaScript) that support regular expressions performs some form of &lt;strong>equivalence reduction&lt;/strong> meaning it tries to reduce the given regular expression into a reduced YET equivalent regular expression. Of course there is no full-proof way of doing this for couple of reasons: (1) There is no way to guarantee that a reduced regular expression is the most efficient regular expression possible. At this moment there is no GENERAL way of proving that.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Faster table rendering</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/faster-table-rendering/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2005 23:55:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/faster-table-rendering/</guid><description>&lt;p>Unlike FireFox, Internet Explorer does not display a table until the complete table data has arrived. This can be looked at both positvely and negatively. The positives are, once the table is rendered it is not modified (width, height, positioning) because all the data has already arrived and IE can properly compute the width and height of the cells and rendered it top-down, right-to-left without making any other adjustments to the cells already displayed. This makes things look a bit better, but this approach is definetly quite slow.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Re-Useable Images</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/re-useable-images/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2005 06:03:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/re-useable-images/</guid><description>&lt;p>I was working on a project last week and part of the work was to create sort of like a template / menu / footer with an opening image. Initally I was positioning the title of the page as a regular h3 but then I thought of something great (I find it to be). &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/reuseable-images/">Take a look at this page&lt;/a> &amp;ndash; if you notice carefully you will see &amp;ldquo;Salman&amp;rsquo;s Blog&amp;rdquo; is just a text. This was done using absolute positioning forcing the div and text to display over the image (with 40% opacity). Absolute positioning shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a concern in this case because it&amp;rsquo;s meant to be used as headers which are constant and therefore have a definite pixel height from the top.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Logos in Photoshop</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/logos-in-photoshop/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jan 2005 14:43:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/logos-in-photoshop/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2005/01/mac-panther-big.jpg">&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2005/01/mac-panther.jpg" alt="Macintosh Panther Logo. Click to enlarge">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Inspired by Macintosh Panther logo, I designed this logo. I started with the letter X of course, then I manually marked the black marks. The second step was to add lighting. I used dodge and burning to do the lighting (while being careful about the nature of light). Then I marked the X layer to Bevel-and-Emboss blending. To give the letter a texture I added a little bit of monochrome gaussian noise. To complete the process I made a copy of the all the layers and inverted vertically then moved the copied layers just below the first X. Then I did a gradient (from white-&amp;gt;transparent) to give the glass reflection effect.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Roomba: Maintaining Direction Part III</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/roomba-maintaining-direction-part-iii/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2004 00:56:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/roomba-maintaining-direction-part-iii/</guid><description>&lt;p>So far I have discussed the following topics:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/vacuum-cleaner/">Introduction to our intelligent Roomba Vacuum cleaner.&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/torus-smart-array-part-ii/">How a torus (smart array) is used to maintain the state of the cleaning surface.&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>Today I will discuss how we managed to maintain the direction we are traveling in.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What we did was to connect two light sensors on both sides of the robot. Then we attached a pinwheel (printed on a paper; see diagram below) attached to the motor using gears, right in front of the sensor. As the motor moved the pinwheel moved and at the same time we could use the sensors to see how many blacks we have seen on the LEFT motor and how many blacks we have seen on the RIGHT motor. A typical straight line direction will see same number of both black and white stripes (because you expect both the left and the right motor to move the same amount of distance causing the same number of black/white alternations); whereas a typical turn (90 degrees) will see more black on one motor compared to the other (once again because during a turn one of the motors is turned off and the other is run at full speed in order to make the turn happen).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Outlook’s vCalender using ASP</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/outlooks-vcalender-using-asp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2004 03:47:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/outlooks-vcalender-using-asp/</guid><description>&lt;p>As part of a continuing effort to build more functional and user-friendly products I am working on an ASP-based vCalendar concept.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Originally I was working on a training enrollment system where users could enroll/drop for a class, standby in a waiting list and things of that nature. My department has been using this product for sometime now and my boss is starting to realize that more people signup than actually showing up. One of the reason for this she argued was they are forgetting that they had a training. One way to remind them of this training is to exploit Outlook&amp;rsquo;s reminder system.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Macintosh Like Light (CSS)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/macintosh-like-light-css/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2004 03:15:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/macintosh-like-light-css/</guid><description>&lt;p>I was working on a new design for something at work and I came up with &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/mac-light/">this&lt;/a> header layout. The background is separated into three images and the center image resizes to fit the content of the header information. Except the images the entire thing is done using CSS.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Torus: Smart Array - Part II</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/torus-smart-array-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2004 03:49:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/torus-smart-array-part-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/vacuum-cleaner/">As I was discussing&lt;/a> I am working on an intelligent vacuum cleaner. In this article I will discuss how we did our state management for the surface the robot is vacuuming.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In order to maintain the state information for the surface, one of things we had for our intelligent Roomba was a char array (VACUUMED, UNKNOWN, BLOCKED are the possible values for each cell). However a simple array wouldn&amp;rsquo;t work because the robot could be physically placed anywhere on the floor, yet our starting position would always be (0,0). This was a problem. One of the solutions proposed and implemented by many others in my class was to &lt;em>shift&lt;/em> the array to accomodate the space in the room. We on the other hand took a different turn; in Microsoft lingo our array was a smart array. Our array acted like a torus which meant that it would wrap around the boundaries. If for instance, the array size is: 60x60 then a reference to the point (70,40) would translate to: (19,40); in this sample case the wrap occured in the x-direction. This took care of the problem of shifting the array. Read on to see the C code for the torus functions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vacuum Cleaner</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/vacuum-cleaner/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2004 00:13:09 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/vacuum-cleaner/</guid><description>&lt;p>For the past few weeks me and a team of three extremely bright computer science graduate students have been working on a vacuum cleaner. The idea is to design a robot that can clean a room &lt;em>efficiently&lt;/em>; the key term here being efficiently. There is an existing product called: &lt;a href="http://www.irobot.com/">Roomba&lt;/a> which sells for about $300.00 dollars and does the same thing we are trying to do &amp;ndash; but it does it zero intelligence. Roomba works by vacuuming a room &lt;strong>long enough&lt;/strong> to gurantee (probabilistically) that at least 90% of the reachable space within a room will be vacuumed. I say reachable because there could be areas in the room which is not reachable and that&amp;rsquo;s not taken into account. Anyway, so in other words to vacuum a 100 sq. ft. room Roomba would spend around 10-15 (regardless of weather it&amp;rsquo;s filled with objects or not &amp;ndash; because it has no way of knowing), where as a human being would easily vacuum the same room in under 2 minutes (83% gain) with perhaps zero unvacuumed areas. The reason Roomba has to vacuum so long is because it has no way of &lt;em>tracking&lt;/em> weather it has been to a specific area in the room (that&amp;rsquo;s partially due to the fact that Roomba runs on only 1~2KB of memory). So a way of guranteeing better coverage is to wonder around in complete disarray for longer hoping to reach that &amp;ldquo;one&amp;rdquo; un-vacuumed area. Of course, no one really complains because who cares if it&amp;rsquo;s vacuuming longer? It&amp;rsquo;s cleaning better right?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Object Databases (ORDBMS)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/object-databases-ordbms/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2004 19:38:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/object-databases-ordbms/</guid><description>&lt;p>ORDBMS - Object Relational, Database Management system. Is an object oriented database management system. The concept at first is a bit suprising since relational database sort of by definition negates the concept of objects. In theory a relational database is a set of relation R; each table, formally known as relations, can be joined (cartesian product) to produce a new relation (which is an improper subset of R1xR2). There are many problems with this scenario. Lets say you want a database that contains sets of points where computers are physically located in a global positioning system. This hypothetical organization contains various departments, a set of departments makes up a local-organization, and a set of local-organization makes up an organization, to make situations worst, each continent can contain several organizations; and there are seven continents. This company is so large they have branches all over the seven continents. The point of this all is to find the minimal net-cost (where cost is distance) for communication between computers. Your product is expected to answers queries of this type:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>JavaScript Performance - Part II</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/javascript-performance-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2004 02:58:36 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/javascript-performance-part-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>As I &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-i">discussed last week&lt;/a> setInterval in general gives better performance compared to setTimeout.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today I will discuss how in order to improve performance, one thread can be used to run multiple animations. Multiple animations come up in several scenarios. For instance, if you have a menu that does some animation onmouseover then although not clear at first this menu system could be running multiple animations at the same time. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s say the animation takes 2 secs to run. Then in this 2 second time frame if the user highlights another menu item then the browser is actually running to threads one for each menu item. This is can bring down the performance of the system quite heavily.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>JavaScript Performance - Part I</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/javascript-performance-part-i/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2004 02:34:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/javascript-performance-part-i/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is the first in a series of articles I plan to write on improving performance in JavaScript heavy web-applications. More specifically I will discuss some of the ways you can improve on JavaScript based animations, reducing object chains, cross-browser DOM, clever ways of writing/designing objects and so on.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Improving on Animations&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>No matter what type of animation it is if it&amp;rsquo;s written using JavaScript it&amp;rsquo;s most likely going to make use of setTimeout or setInterval. Both of these function work like a timeline in Flash and therefore it&amp;rsquo;s ideal for doing animations. To begin with setInterval is much faster than setTimeout. The reason is setInterval causes a function to continously run until it&amp;rsquo;s stopped using clearInterval, where as setTimeout runs a function after a given time and stops; therefore if you wanted to animate something using setTimeout you would somehow have to keep calling setTimeout (until the animation ended) where as in setInterval this is done only once. The down-side of this is setInterval is supported only by Internet Explorer so to get &lt;strong>really&lt;/strong> high performance you might want to write one version (separate files) of your JavaScript that&amp;rsquo;s geard towards Internet Explorer and another for Netscape (which supports setTimeout). &lt;em>Next time I will discuss how to run multiple animations at once using one-thread (or one setTimeout or setInterval).&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using XSLT to view graphical poll results</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-xslt-to-view-graphical-poll-results/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2004 04:18:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/using-xslt-to-view-graphical-poll-results/</guid><description>&lt;p>How I came to this is not relevant I think, so I will jump straight to the examples. The idea was to convert &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/poll-data-raw.xml">this XML document&lt;/a> to produce &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/poll-results.xml">this output&lt;/a>. So I set out to do it &amp;ndash; and it was finally done using &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/poll-transform.xsl">this XSLT stylesheet&lt;/a>. The idea is quite basic. Count the number of &amp;lsquo;I agree&amp;rsquo; responses and store it in a variable. Count the number of &amp;lsquo;I disagree&amp;rsquo; responses and store it into another variable, and so on&amp;hellip; Once that&amp;rsquo;s done, the count values are multiplied with the expansion factor (&lt;em>variable: efactor&lt;/em>) and this number is set to the height of a div element. That&amp;rsquo;s all. Let&amp;rsquo;s all resolute to producing a standardized web!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Solution to Line Tracker</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/solution-to-line-tracker/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Oct 2004 01:17:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/solution-to-line-tracker/</guid><description>&lt;p>In my &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/line-tracker/">previous post&lt;/a> I discussed an algorithm that it is much better than the &lt;em>general&lt;/em> line following algorithm that one might think of at first. Last night I implemented the algorithm with NQC with descent results. Here&amp;rsquo;s the solution:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-c" data-lang="c">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm">/***********************************************
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm"> * Salman Quazi
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm"> * CS-595EA
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm"> * Date: September 19, 2004
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm">***********************************************/&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm">/* Constant Definitions */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define SENSOR SENSOR_1
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define LEFT_MOTOR OUT_C
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define RIGHT_MOTOR OUT_A
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm">/* Speed settings */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define NORMAL_SPEED 7
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define TURN_SPEED 2
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define DELAY 20
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm">/* This setting depends on several conditions like: lighting, contrast between the tape and the floor ... */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define LINE_COLOR 768
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">#define FLOOR_COLOR 710
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cp">&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">eye&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm">/* I have been thinking about taking the average color of the
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="cm">floor and the black tape for more reliable results */&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">average_color&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LINE_COLOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">FLOOR_COLOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mi">2&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">task&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nf">main&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">()&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">SetPower&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">NORMAL_SPEED&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">SetPower&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">NORMAL_SPEED&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">OnFwd&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">while&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nb">true&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="n">eye&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">SENSOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">SelectDisplay&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">DISPLAY_SENSOR_1&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">if&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">eye&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;lt;=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">FLOOR_COLOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">SetPower&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">TURN_SPEED&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">Fwd&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">Rev&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">On&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">while&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">SENSOR&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;lt;=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">FLOOR_COLOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">else&lt;/span> &lt;span class="k">if&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">eye&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;gt;=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">LINE_COLOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">)&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">{&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">SetPower&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">TURN_SPEED&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">Fwd&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">Rev&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">On&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">while&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">SENSOR&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">&amp;gt;=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">LINE_COLOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">else&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="k">continue&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">SetPower&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">NORMAL_SPEED&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">Fwd&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">Fwd&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">On&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">LEFT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="n">RIGHT_MOTOR&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">);&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">}&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This was compiled with &lt;a href="http://bricxcc.sourceforge.net/nqc/release/index.html">NQC version 2.5 r3&lt;/a> on &lt;a href="http://mindstorms.lego.com/support/en/ris20.asp">RCX 2.0&lt;/a> (on a Windows 2000 Professional system).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Line Tracker</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/line-tracker/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Sep 2004 16:59:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/line-tracker/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have a project due in few weeks. The idea of the project is that the LEGO mindstorm has to follow a black line on the floor. So I started thinking about this problem and my initial approach was the following: I assume my robot starts ON the black line. So it starts traveling forward and continues until it finds white (which is the floor). At this point it has to turn but which way? To the left or to the right? Perhaps it picks either one of those in random (LEFT or RIGHT) and tries to find black, if it can&amp;rsquo;t find black it turns again and &lt;strong>hopes&lt;/strong> to find black in the opposite direction (otherwise it&amp;rsquo;s completely lost). This process seems overly complicated and extremely un-reliable. More importantly if [this is not required in my project] mindstorm had to go the finishing line in the earliest possible time then the above approach would certainly fail because it would have to &lt;strong>search&lt;/strong> the black line as opposed to &lt;strong>&lt;em>follow&lt;/em>&lt;/strong> the black line. So I had to think of a different approach and I came up with the following: Follow one of the edges of the black line (rather than the whole black line). Even before starting to think about this problem I started to see some of the program&amp;rsquo;s benefits. So let&amp;rsquo;s say I choose to follow the right edge, then the robot should look to the left for white and right for black. Very elegant. The robot would either to make a right or a left. If after turning a little (let&amp;rsquo;s say 5 radians) it finds black it continues to turn in that direction until it finds the edge and then continues in that direction. I am currently working on the latter algorithm and will soon post the C code (&lt;em>actually NQC code&lt;/em>) for you guys.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dynamic contents</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/dynamic-contents/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2004 03:04:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/dynamic-contents/</guid><description>&lt;p>Generating dynamic contents can be a great way to allow your users to find information quickly. In &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/dynamic-index.php">this example&lt;/a> the page headlines menu option was created dynamically (using JavaScript). In this case the contents was generated dynamically using H3 tags it can be very easily modified to read H1,H2, IMG, IFRAME, SPAN, DIV or any other tag that comes to mind (except perhaps BR :-))&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Date Format (using XSLT)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/date-format-using-xslt/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2004 22:31:59 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/date-format-using-xslt/</guid><description>&lt;p>It was sort of surprising to find out that XSLT does not have any predefined date formatting function. So after spending sometime on my own I came up with this solution:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-xslt" data-lang="xslt">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:template&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;format-date&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:param&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;date&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:variable&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;monthName&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;substring-before($date, &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;)&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:variable&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;day&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;substring-before(substring-after($date, &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;), &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;)&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:variable&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;year&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;substring-after(substring-after($date, &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;), &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;)&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:variable&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;month&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;substring(substring-after(&amp;#39;01Jan02Feb03Mar04Apr05May06Jun07Jul08Aug09Sep10Oct11Nov12Dec&amp;#39;, $monthName), 1, 3)&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:value-of&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;concat($month, &amp;#39;, &amp;#39;, $year)&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:template&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>You can call this function like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-xslt" data-lang="xslt">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:call-template&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;format-date&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:with-param&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;date&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">select&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;@date&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;/&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">xsl:call-template&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Where &lt;code>@date&lt;/code> is the date string (in this case the date attribute) you want to format. For instance this XSLT function rewrites dates written in this format: 06/23/2004 to. Jan. 2004. If you want to include the day in the resulting date, just modify the &lt;code>xsl:value-of&lt;/code> concat line and concat the day also.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Search for PGP key given a keyserver</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/search-for-pgp-key-given-a-keyserver/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2004 17:37:24 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/search-for-pgp-key-given-a-keyserver/</guid><description>&lt;p>In Linux just do this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">gpg --keyserver &lt;span class="s2">&amp;#34;ldap://certserver.pgp.com&amp;#34;&lt;/span> --search-keys &lt;span class="s2">&amp;#34;&amp;lt;e-mail address&amp;gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Note the option: &amp;ndash;keyserver can be other Keyservers like the &lt;a href="http://pgp.mit.edu/">MIT Key Server&lt;/a> (pgp.mit.edu).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>JavaScript Buffering - Offscreen</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/javascript-buffering-offscreen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2004 14:39:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/javascript-buffering-offscreen/</guid><description>&lt;p>Just before I go to bed I thought I make an interesting post. The other day I worked on a site for a client; like most of my sites it was very heavy on style sheet (meaning most of the alignments and things were done with style sheet rather than tables, etc.) So what would happen is the page would load without style sheet for a sec. and then the style sheet would be applied. So for a split second the client would have to see the page without the style sheet &amp;ndash; which doesn&amp;rsquo;t look professional.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sequential Preloading..</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/sequential-preloading/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2004 14:45:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/sequential-preloading/</guid><description>&lt;p>How do you make certain JavaScript sequentially preloads your images? For instance if you have 10 images and the size of image 9 is the smallest then it&amp;rsquo;s most likely JavaScript (internet explorer rather) will load image 9 first. Then the second smallest or perhaps in no true order. However there are times when you need to make certain the images are loaded in sequence&amp;hellip;. The following accomplishes this &amp;ndash; figured it out after a lot of problems:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Speaking about events technically</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/speaking-about-events-technically/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2004 05:31:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/speaking-about-events-technically/</guid><description>&lt;p>The other day I was working on something in JavaScript and I thought I would share that with you. Before I can begin though I have to describe the scenario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I have an image in an HTML page (lets call it: MyImage). I dynamically attach an event to the Image&amp;rsquo;s onload method. Due to other events on the page MyImage&amp;rsquo;s SRC attribute gets changed to something else. Now logically the onload event should execute again once the new SRC element gets loaded. But guess what? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t. onload is known as a: &amp;ldquo;recursive descent&amp;rdquo; event meaning it descends recursively from the BODY; so unless the BODY&amp;rsquo;s onload event doesn&amp;rsquo;t change (which doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen until reload/refresh) MyImage&amp;rsquo;s onload event does not fire.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Embedded Software</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/embedded-software/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Jun 2004 05:49:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/embedded-software/</guid><description>&lt;p>Interesting semester coming up for me. As some of you may know I am starting (at least partially) my masters in Computer Science. After much thought. I have decided to focus on the field of: Embedded Software Development. Embedded applications are everywhere. When you use your microwave, drive your car, program your tv, program you DVD player and on and on. Almost all household devices have some software embedded into it. That&amp;rsquo;s how it functions. Of course there has to be someone writing those softwares. I will be that person. About 10 years ago however, a company would hire an Electrical Engineer or a Computer Engineer to do this task. But recently there has been some advancements where Computer Scientists can design the software as if they were writing it for the PC. Then a third party software such as: VeriLog takes the assembly of the software (with the help of some hardware such as EP-ROM writers) and takes care of writing to the device so that the device can function. Of course each devices has to supply an API that can be used to manipulate or get access to information from the actual device. But most devices these days do.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Alpha Beta Searching</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/alpha-beta-searching/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2004 04:58:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/alpha-beta-searching/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have a test tonight. I am fairly certain I will get an A; however, there is only one thing that I am unsure about: AlphaBeta searching. So I went online and read couple of books. Here&amp;rsquo;s my understanding (in brief of course): AlphaBeta searching is an optimized searching model based on MinMax searching (or MiniMax search). So to understand AlphaBeta searching we must first understand MinMax searching. MinMax searching can be applied on game trees (if you are not familiar with game trees then please &lt;a href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;q=Game+Trees">go here&lt;/a>). The MinMax comes from the fact that the searching algorithm alternates between searching for a maximum value, and a minimum value. For instance, if it&amp;rsquo;s the computers move then the computer searches for a maximum node (when I refer to maximum I am referring to the move-value which is the heuristic value for that move). On the other hand, when it turn for the opponents move the computer searches for a MIN value and so on. AlphaBeta searching improves on the MinMax algorithm with the following assumption. Lets say you know a node K is better than node K&amp;rsquo; and you can prove that the best possible move can be K then how much better is K than K&amp;rsquo; is absolutely irrelivant because no matter what value K&amp;rsquo; is you will end up choosing K because K is the best move. Therefore if K&amp;rsquo; had a subtree none of that needs to be computed which eventually saves tremendous amount of time.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Unique Elements (in XSLT)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/unique-elements-in-xslt/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2004 23:58:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/unique-elements-in-xslt/</guid><description>&lt;p>At work I have this XML document that lists all the employees along with their responsiblities. The general format looks something like this (staff.xml):&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-xml" data-lang="xml">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;ga-staff&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;department&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">title=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Administration&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span>Director, Corporate Accounting&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span>...&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span>...&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;email&amp;gt;&lt;/span>...&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/email&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span>Manager&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span>...&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span>...&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;email&amp;gt;&lt;/span>...&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/email&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/department&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;department&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">title=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> ...
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/department&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nt">&amp;lt;/ga-staff&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>I was asked to generate a flat (meaning only their name, phone and e-mail) output (sorted by name) of all the staffs in our department. The only problem with using (existing) staff.xml is that there are certain employees who have multiple responsiblities, so their name appears more than once. Of course I cannot display their name more than once in the flat output. That makes no sense. The output would be something like this:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Kolmogorov Complexity</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/kolmogorov-complexity/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2004 16:29:01 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/kolmogorov-complexity/</guid><description>&lt;p>A computer science/mathematics student learns various ways of measuring complexity of a problem. I feel this is an extremely important field because it allows us to measure the difficulty-level (or complexity of a problem). Without it, it would be like trying to lift a box without knowing how much it weighs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For instance, how complex is it to sort N numbers? Using standard notation it turns out the best possible solution can be: O(n*lg(n)) (we can prove that this is the best possible solution). This is the so-called: Big-O notation; something a freshman/sophomore CS student learns.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CSS: word-wrap</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/css-word-wrap/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2004 23:58:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/css-word-wrap/</guid><description>&lt;p>You will notice this blog site will not overflow in the x-direction no matter what resolution you view this site in (I tried upto 640x480). When you have a div area and you are using PRE or XMP to view formatted contents (like I do in this page to view code) within that div &amp;ndash; this would be almost impossible to do. Here&amp;rsquo;s the reason: unless otherwise stated a PRE or an XMP is displayed as is. Take a look at &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/longpre.php">this page&lt;/a> for instance. See how it overflows? If you had a shorter viewing area the overflow would be even greater. The solution is to explicitly say to allow word breaks. Take a look at &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/longpre-fixed.php">this page&lt;/a>. It does not overflow anymore (assuming you are using IE). View the code to see the difference.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Power of PROLOG</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/power-of-prolog/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2004 18:01:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/power-of-prolog/</guid><description>&lt;p>Here&amp;rsquo;s yet another example of the power available to you in PROLOG. Let&amp;rsquo;s consider this simultaneous equation:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-prolog" data-lang="prolog">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="mi">3&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">x&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">4&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">y&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">17&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="mi">4&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">x&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">3&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">y&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">18&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>In PROLOG I can find the values of X and Y just like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-prolog" data-lang="prolog">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nf">compute&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">X&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">Y&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">):-&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="nf">fd_domain&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">([&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">X&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">Y&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">],&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mi">0&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mi">1000&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">),&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="mi">3&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">*&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">X&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">4&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">*&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">Y&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">#=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">17&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl"> &lt;span class="mi">4&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">*&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">X&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">3&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">*&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">Y&lt;/span> &lt;span class="s">#=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mf">18.&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>That almost seems like I am joking &amp;ndash; but I am really not. That 3 lines of code will find all solutions to X and Y. So I tried the following:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-prolog" data-lang="prolog">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="s">?-&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nf">compute&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">(&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">A&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">,&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">B&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">).&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nv">A&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">3&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nv">B&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">2&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="s">yes&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>I should note, the values of X and Y are between 0&amp;hellip;1000 (integers). All Contraint Logic Problems (CLPs) require a finite domain. That&amp;rsquo;s why they are sometimes referred to as: Finite Domain (FD) Problems. Since CLP is not standardized each compiler supports FDs differently. I am in this case using &lt;a href="http://pauillac.inria.fr/~diaz/gnu-prolog/">GNU Prolog&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Constraint Logic Programming</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/constraint-logic-programming/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2004 06:07:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/constraint-logic-programming/</guid><description>&lt;p>PROLOG can is one of many languages that can be used to perform Constraint Logic Programming (CLP). Just like C++ and Visual Basic can be used to program Object Oriented Programs (OOP). Same idea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The idea behind CLP is the following: give contraints to a problem and request all solutions. For instance, if I had:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-prolog" data-lang="prolog">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nv">X&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">+&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nv">Y&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="mi">100&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Suppose I wanted to find all the integer solutions to this problem it would be very difficult to code in a regular language (not so much in this specific case because it&amp;rsquo;s too simple, but in general). Because the programmer would have to manually control backtracking and assignment and all sorts of stuff. However take a look at this PROLOG program:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hiding Elements During Printing</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/hiding-elements-during-printing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2004 02:15:13 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/hiding-elements-during-printing/</guid><description>&lt;p>I work in an environment where my collegues surrounding me strongly believe there is no difference between &amp;ldquo;Microsoft Excel&amp;rdquo; and the web. One of the arguments I almost always hear: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;why can&amp;rsquo;t you do it? it can be done in excel &amp;ndash; see!&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So that&amp;rsquo;s how it all started; Excel apparently has a feature that allows a user to hide certain elements from the spreadsheet during print-out; I am not sure how exactly it&amp;rsquo;s done, I am not an Excel expert.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Volume Backup</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/volume-backup/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Apr 2004 16:23:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/volume-backup/</guid><description>&lt;p>I am trying to work on a system/method to perform incremental backup over the network (using SAMBA). Here are some of the steps I have taken&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First I decided on the set of data that needs to be backed up. Since the very beginning all my data files (such as documents, programs, musics and so on) are kept in a completely separate drive. This drive (although large in size) is used only for my personal stuff and I never install anything or create any dependencies on this drive. This helps me be independent in case of an operating system crash.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Random Numbers</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/random-numbers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2004 15:41:30 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/random-numbers/</guid><description>&lt;p>There are tons of masters, PhD thesis written on generating uniform (as in uniform distribution) random numbers using a computer. The problem with generating random numbers is finding a true source of entropy. The usual rand() or RND function found in most languages use the system clock as the source of entropy. This is perhaps the worst method of generating a random number; the reason being the change of entropy is predictable (because the change of time is predictable &amp;ndash; the millisecond counter changes 1/1000 sec). One technique (a technique used by PGP) uses other random sources from your computer. For instance mouse movements, thread counts or whatever else. The above techniques works wonders if you only want to generate small sets of random numbers. If you want to generate larger sets then you start to see recognizable patterns (this happens perhaps because you start of have predictable mouse movements, predictable thread counts and so on). I am working on a project that requires large sets of random numbers with low levels of predictability (note this level is not to be confused with the entropy value that is often paired with random numbers; what I am referring to here is the chi-square value). So as I was researching around the internet I came across this web-site: &lt;a href="http://www.random.org/">www.random.org&lt;/a>. All they do is produce random numbers. The way the &lt;a href="http://www.random.org/">random.org&lt;/a> random number generator works is quite simple. A radio is tuned into a frequency where nobody is broadcasting. The atmospheric noise picked up by the receiver is fed into a Sun SPARC workstation through the microphone port where it is sampled by a program as an eight bit mono signal at a frequency of 8KHz. The upper seven bits of each sample are discarded immediately and the remaining bits are gathered and turned into a stream of bits with a high content of entropy. Skew correction is performed on the bit stream, in order to ensure that there is an approximately even distribution of 0s and 1s. Recently they added a &lt;a href="http://www.random.org/soap.html">SOAP interface&lt;/a> to their application; so what I will do is use their SOAP interface to receive some data and use that for my application. I will post the link to the resulting page as soon as I am done.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Unification</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/unification/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2004 18:51:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/unification/</guid><description>&lt;p>In PROLOG there is an idea called: unification. It&amp;rsquo;s similar to setting a variable to something but there are certainly several difference (otherwise it would be called assignment). One major difference in unification is pattern matching. For instance if I had the following code segment in PROLOG&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="nx">X&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">/&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">Y&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">10&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">/&lt;/span> &lt;span class="nx">a&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Then the variable X will be assigned 10 and the variable Y will be assigned a. This is very powerful tool. Unification however has some limitations. For instance, unification with bounds-check (the default unification in PROLOG) won&amp;rsquo;t allow one to do the following.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>AccessKey</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/accesskey/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2004 21:58:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/accesskey/</guid><description>&lt;p>Almost all HTML/XHTML tags have an attribute called: accesskey. What this does is allows the programmer to assign key-codes to elements in the page. For instance, if I did this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">Search: &lt;span class="p">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span class="nt">input&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">type&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;text&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">name&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;Search&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">value&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="na">access&lt;/span>&lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span>&lt;span class="s">&amp;#34;S&amp;#34;&lt;/span> &lt;span class="p">/&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Then the user could enter: ALT+S to jump to this field no matter where they are on the page. This feature can make a web-site very user friendly. For instance to jump to search field on this page enter: ALT+4.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SICP</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/sicp/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2004 21:25:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/sicp/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book.html">Structure and Interpretaition of Computer Program&lt;/a> is often considered one of the greatest books written on LISP or generally program structure (as the name suggests). Strangely enough the book is now available freely (through MIT) at: &lt;a href="http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book.html">http://mitpress.mit.edu/sicp/full-text/book/book.html&lt;/a> One of my favorite quotes happens to be written in the Preface section of the first edition of this book: &amp;ldquo;Programs must be written for people to read, and only incidentally for machines to execute.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Thinking in C++</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/thinking-in-c/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2004 08:21:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/thinking-in-c/</guid><description>&lt;p>I found &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2004/03/thinking_cpp.pdf">this&lt;/a> great book only it&amp;rsquo;s called: Thinking in C++. It&amp;rsquo;s a complete 1200+ pages book for FREE. &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2004/03/thinking_cpp.pdf">Download&lt;/a> it!&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bit Operations</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/bit-operations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2004 23:30:07 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/bit-operations/</guid><description>&lt;p>A friend of mine once asked me what the following code does.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-c" data-lang="c">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="k">register&lt;/span> &lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">a&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">a&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">^=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">a&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>After a bit of thought I realized that &amp;ldquo;a&amp;rdquo; gets initialized to zero. But why do it that way when you can do it like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma">&lt;code class="language-c" data-lang="c">&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="kt">int&lt;/span> &lt;span class="n">a&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span class="line">&lt;span class="cl">&lt;span class="n">a&lt;/span> &lt;span class="o">=&lt;/span> &lt;span class="mi">0&lt;/span>&lt;span class="p">;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The answer lies in the machine translation for each of these segments. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at it one piece at a time. The first code segment requests &amp;ldquo;a&amp;rdquo; to be part of one of the several general paramenter registers in the CPU. If that&amp;rsquo;s granted then the statement a^=a; is simple XOR edx, eax.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>PROLOG</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/prolog/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2004 07:01:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/prolog/</guid><description>&lt;p>This semester I am taking a course in PROLOG. It has been almost 5 weeks now since I have been taking this course; and I strongly believe that every programmer should take at least one course in a logic programming class. I feel a course of this type will open the mind so greatly that it will not only help one program in other languages but help in several other aspects of one&amp;rsquo;s life. In institutions like Caltech and MIT, PROLOG is a required course for any computer science students. Unfortunately that&amp;rsquo;s not the case in my university (@ CSUN). A one paragraph idea behind PROLOG is the following: thinking of logic as a method of computation. In all other structured/object-oriented you cannot explicitly supply the core-logic &amp;ndash; instead you have to find an algorithm that when followed will compute something logical. There is a vast difference between the two. They require completely different method of thinking. One of these days I will post a sample code written in PROLOG and perhaps to compare the same program in C#.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Verifying your site is running?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/verifying-your-site-is-running/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2004 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/en/blog/verifying-your-site-is-running/</guid><description>&lt;p>This question often comes up-how do you make sure that your site is running? One solution is to run tools like &lt;a href="http://www.ipswitch.com/products/whatsup/index.asp">WhatsUp Gold&lt;/a> that monitors your IIS service status, SQL service status etc. As long as these services respond as saying they are running, WhatsUp gold is happy. But unfortunately, the fact that these services are running does not mean that your website is functioning to the public. For example if you have a page that depends on an external web service, and for some reason the external web service is down, then your page will not respond and will eventually time out. To the public your site is down. WhatsUp gold is not necessarily going to check for that. I say not necessarily because it is possible to have WhatsUp gold monitor HTTP status, but that creates a strong coupling between WhatsUp gold and generic application development.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>