<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Performance on Salman Quazi</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/tags/performance/</link><description>Recent content in Performance on Salman Quazi</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>Salman Quazi</managingEditor><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 08:57:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.salmanq.com/tags/performance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>.NET and Node.JS - Performance Comparison (Updated)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/net-and-node-js-performance-comparison/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 08:57:39 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/net-and-node-js-performance-comparison/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (3/31/2013 - 11:41 PM PST):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article has been updated! As most readers have commented the node.js async package is not asynchronous, which is what the original article was based on. I made an assumption I should not have. I have since rerun the tests taking this into account, as well as some of the changes recommended by &lt;a href="http://guillaume86.calepin.co/dotnet-vs-nodejs-performance.html"&gt;Guillaume Lecomte&lt;/a&gt;. I have decided to update this existing post so that there&amp;rsquo;s no confusion in the future with the data. Thank you everyone for all the comments, posts and keeping me sane.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Improving Wordpress site speed on IIS</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/improving-wordpress-site-speed-on-iis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 19:03:14 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/improving-wordpress-site-speed-on-iis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I did when I started this blog was to change the way static files are cached by IIS to improve site speed. Static files are things that aren&amp;rsquo;t going to change, things like CSS, JavaScript, images, documents, and so on. With IIS this is actually quite easy to achieve, you can start by making the following change to your web.config:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-xml" data-lang="xml"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;system.webServer&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;staticContent&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;clientCache&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;cacheControlMode=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;UseMaxAge&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;cacheControlMaxAge=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;7.00:00:00&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/staticContent&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/system.webServer&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a set of file extensions that&amp;rsquo;s already mapped to staticContent - so IIS only applies this change to all static contents. Also notice that we are caching the content on the client side. This means returning visitors will see a performance boost and we cache it for 7 days on the client side. If you have file extensions that are not part of the standard staticContent extension list, you can easily add it by doing:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The trailing slash</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/the-trailing-slash/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2005 00:47:36 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/the-trailing-slash/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a simple change as adding a slash may improve the performance of your web-applications. Consider this: the link &lt;a href="http://www.salmanq.com"&gt;www.salmanq.com&lt;/a&gt; is slower than &lt;a href="http://www.salmanq.com/"&gt;www.salmanq.com/&lt;/a&gt; (the only difference being the trailing slash). They will both work but the latter is faster. When this link: &lt;a href="https://www.onupol.com"&gt;www.onupol.com&lt;/a&gt; is followed the web-server returns a 301 (Moved Permanently) pointing to &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/"&gt;www.salmanq.com/&lt;/a&gt; that&amp;rsquo;s one extra round trip to and from the server per link. If you have a site that&amp;rsquo;s running without the trailing slash and you have 10K+ visitors you will certainly start to feel the consequence.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Optimizing Regular Expressions</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/optimizing-regular-expressions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Feb 2005 16:23:02 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/optimizing-regular-expressions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Optimizing regular expressions is an exceptionally complex field. A vast majority of the problems within this field is &lt;code&gt;NP&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;NP-COMPLETE&lt;/code&gt;. Meaning that their solutions cannot be bound (time/space) under any definite polynomial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All APIs (such as: .NET, PHP, ASP (classic VB really), JavaScript) that support regular expressions performs some form of &lt;strong&gt;equivalence reduction&lt;/strong&gt; meaning it tries to reduce the given regular expression into a reduced YET equivalent regular expression. Of course there is no full-proof way of doing this for couple of reasons: (1) There is no way to guarantee that a reduced regular expression is the most efficient regular expression possible. At this moment there is no GENERAL way of proving that.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Faster table rendering</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/faster-table-rendering/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2005 23:55:26 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/faster-table-rendering/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Unlike FireFox, Internet Explorer does not display a table until the complete table data has arrived. This can be looked at both positvely and negatively. The positives are, once the table is rendered it is not modified (width, height, positioning) because all the data has already arrived and IE can properly compute the width and height of the cells and rendered it top-down, right-to-left without making any other adjustments to the cells already displayed. This makes things look a bit better, but this approach is definetly quite slow.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Performance - Part II</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2004 02:58:36 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As I &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-i"&gt;discussed last week&lt;/a&gt; setInterval in general gives better performance compared to setTimeout.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I will discuss how in order to improve performance, one thread can be used to run multiple animations. Multiple animations come up in several scenarios. For instance, if you have a menu that does some animation onmouseover then although not clear at first this menu system could be running multiple animations at the same time. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s say the animation takes 2 secs to run. Then in this 2 second time frame if the user highlights another menu item then the browser is actually running to threads one for each menu item. This is can bring down the performance of the system quite heavily.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Performance - Part I</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-i/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2004 02:34:33 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-i/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first in a series of articles I plan to write on improving performance in JavaScript heavy web-applications. More specifically I will discuss some of the ways you can improve on JavaScript based animations, reducing object chains, cross-browser DOM, clever ways of writing/designing objects and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improving on Animations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what type of animation it is if it&amp;rsquo;s written using JavaScript it&amp;rsquo;s most likely going to make use of setTimeout or setInterval. Both of these function work like a timeline in Flash and therefore it&amp;rsquo;s ideal for doing animations. To begin with setInterval is much faster than setTimeout. The reason is setInterval causes a function to continously run until it&amp;rsquo;s stopped using clearInterval, where as setTimeout runs a function after a given time and stops; therefore if you wanted to animate something using setTimeout you would somehow have to keep calling setTimeout (until the animation ended) where as in setInterval this is done only once. The down-side of this is setInterval is supported only by Internet Explorer so to get &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; high performance you might want to write one version (separate files) of your JavaScript that&amp;rsquo;s geard towards Internet Explorer and another for Netscape (which supports setTimeout). &lt;em&gt;Next time I will discuss how to run multiple animations at once using one-thread (or one setTimeout or setInterval).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Buffering - Offscreen</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-buffering-offscreen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2004 14:39:12 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-buffering-offscreen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Just before I go to bed I thought I make an interesting post. The other day I worked on a site for a client; like most of my sites it was very heavy on style sheet (meaning most of the alignments and things were done with style sheet rather than tables, etc.) So what would happen is the page would load without style sheet for a sec. and then the style sheet would be applied. So for a split second the client would have to see the page without the style sheet &amp;ndash; which doesn&amp;rsquo;t look professional.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bit Operations</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/bit-operations/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2004 23:30:07 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/bit-operations/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine once asked me what the following code does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-c" data-lang="c"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;register&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;^=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;After a bit of thought I realized that &amp;ldquo;a&amp;rdquo; gets initialized to zero. But why do it that way when you can do it like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-c" data-lang="c"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;The answer lies in the machine translation for each of these segments. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at it one piece at a time. The first code segment requests &amp;ldquo;a&amp;rdquo; to be part of one of the several general paramenter registers in the CPU. If that&amp;rsquo;s granted then the statement a^=a; is simple XOR edx, eax.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>