<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Architecture on Salman Quazi</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/tags/architecture/</link><description>Recent content in Architecture on Salman Quazi</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>Salman Quazi</managingEditor><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 05:19:13 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.salmanq.com/tags/architecture/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Building a service execution pipeline</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/building-a-service-execution-pipeline/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2013 05:19:13 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/building-a-service-execution-pipeline/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Most software built today have a notion of a client and a service. This is even more true with mobile/web applications because you want your client apps to do as little as possible, and your service to do most of the heavy lifting. This allows you to improve your service without requiring constant client updates. Also since you have a single service that serves potentially various native clients (iOS, Android, or Windows Phone), being able to update it independently of your users gives you a clear competitive edge. So today I want to focus on building a service based on this notion of a &amp;ldquo;pipeline&amp;rdquo;. Most .NET client/service frameworks already have this concept. For instance, Windows Communication Foundation (WCF) has an execution pipeline, and so does ASP.NET. This allows you to extend the behavior of these frameworks at various points during the execution. But that&amp;rsquo;s not really what I want to talk about today. I want to talk about how &lt;em&gt;you can build&lt;/em&gt; your services such that you can add/remove functionality using a pipeline-style execution. As we are talking about the implementation of this pipeline I also want to take this opportunity to discuss good software design practices, and it&amp;rsquo;s uses. &lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/04/service-execution-pipeline.png" alt="service-execution-pipeline"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Composition over Inheritance</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/composition-over-inheritance/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 01:37:44 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/composition-over-inheritance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There are several ways to extend the behavior of a class. One of my preferred approach to extending behaviors is composition, and that is what we are going to talk about today. Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a simple example of inheritance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-csharp" data-lang="csharp"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Search&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;ISearch&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;IEnumerable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;SearchResults&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Search&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Query&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;q&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="kd"&gt;public&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;Related&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Search&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;IEnumerable&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;RelatedEntities&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Related&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;Query&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;q&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;So in this simple example, we extend Search and create Related - which provides some additional functionality. But a completely different approach which provides same results is to use composition:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part III</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-iii/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 06:39:59 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-iii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We are at the finale of this three part series. &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/"&gt;In part I&lt;/a&gt; we discussed the MVVM design pattern, &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/"&gt;in part II&lt;/a&gt; we looked at the overall architecture and how the server side fits into the picture. In this article we are going to look at the client side of this and close with some final thoughts. The best place to start with the client is the HTML - so here&amp;rsquo;s the part of the HTML that&amp;rsquo;s interesting:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part II</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 04:23:51 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/"&gt;Last time we looked at what the MVVM pattern was&lt;/a&gt;, and how it is used today in XAML-based applications. Today we are going to take a step further and build a mechanism to use the MVVM pattern on traditional web applications. Imagine how powerful it would be if your UI could evolve independently. We are going to build a simple web application that will display top 5 &amp;ldquo;memory intensive&amp;rdquo; processes on the server side, and here&amp;rsquo;s our basic architecture: &lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/03/mvvm-web-pattern.png" alt="MVVM Architecture for Web Applications"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How do you test your software?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/how-do-you-test-your-software/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2013 15:09:40 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/how-do-you-test-your-software/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;There seems to be two types of developers out there. One that believes in integration tests, and the other that believes in both unit and integration tests. Integration tests are tests that execute everything as if they were real &amp;ldquo;transactions&amp;rdquo; only to verify the expected results. For instance, if you were building a web application that managed a list of employees and their supervisors. Your integration test would probably add an employee to the database (actually add it), and then read it back from that database, and so on (from a test database of course). There&amp;rsquo;s nothing wrong this, and in fact I would argue these types of tests are great. You need to write integration tests that exercise your entire stack. Without it would be like exercising without doing cardio. What differentiates a unit test from other types of tests is that you test a &amp;ldquo;unit&amp;rdquo; of your application alone. Now what that unit is, is up to you. But the point is you take a &lt;em&gt;part&lt;/em&gt; of your application and test it in &lt;em&gt;isolation&lt;/em&gt;. That part could be a class, it could be multiple sets of classes, but not your application as a whole - otherwise it would become an integration test. Seems like we have a conundrum here. We just argued that a integration test, tests everything, end-to-end, the entire stack &amp;ndash; and a unit test, tests a part of the application in isolation. Isn&amp;rsquo;t integration test then a superset of unit tests? And there is where the confusion lies. &lt;strong&gt;So why write unit tests?&lt;/strong&gt; While it is true that unit tests can often uncover bugs in the code, in reality unit tests actually help discover a far bigger problem; and that is design of your system. Unit tests can discover design issues if left unaddressed could severely impact your velocity to adapt to change. I would argue that if you can write proper tests for your system with good code coverage, then you have a well designed, cohesive system. Now unit testing alone is no silver bullet to design verification, but it&amp;rsquo;s pretty close. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a really simple example:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part I</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 09:01:15 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this series I will be discussing how the MVVM pattern can be used for almost any type of web application. MVVM (a variant on the MVP pattern) - is a really powerful pattern that can be used in UI applications. Traditionally these UI applications has been WPF and Silverlight. In this article I will show you how you can use the same principles to build web applications. With MVVM you have the following three ideas:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Brief introduction to PRISM</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/brief-introduction-to-prism/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2011 14:55:10 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/brief-introduction-to-prism/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Before I go into the technical details of this article. I want to provide some context for this discussion. So we are using &lt;a href="http://compositewpf.codeplex.com/"&gt;PRISM&lt;/a&gt; to develop a user-interface (UI) platform in the context of a Silverlight (but they apply to WPF also). The idea behind the UI platform is we will provide the basic functional look and feel and various plumbing (such as security, service encapsulation, messaging and exception handling, among others) and allow others to develop modules/components on top. PRISM allows us to do this quite well. Let’s assume for a second, you have a system where a user can initiate an order, and then track the shipment status of that order. PRISM allows us to separate the concerns of this applications into two distinct tasks. (1) ordering, and (2) shipment tracking (and perhaps even further, but let’s keep it simple). Each of these could be developed as separate modules, and therefore separate DLLs, and possibly by separate teams. In the end, with PRISM, we can &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;dynamically compose&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; these at runtime even though they are independent components. So if you can imagine for a second, all the base functionality that we talked earlier is hosted in a component itself usually referred to as the Shell. The Shell is like the hosting application, where everything comes together. If there’s any resemblance to web applications, as Masterpage is to a ASP.NET page, a Shell is to a Silverlight/WPF application. That’s one way to look at it. So that’s the general overview for our discussion. And you can get a lot of good content about PRISM from Karl Shifflett, John Papa. With PRISM (and also few other technologies like MEF) what we are able to do is we are able to surface modules on the fly based on a modules catalog (one of many ways). One key architectural decision we made early on was that the Shell would be independent of the modules – meaning the Shell does not have any strong references to the modules. This allows us to introduce new modules without actually recompiling the Shell. But many examples out there do exactly that, they either (1) add strong references to Modules from the Shell or (2) they use something known as a ModulesCatalog file. Which is a XAML file that weakly defines the modules list. But again, the ModulesCatalog.xaml file is backed into the Shell – and therefore part of the XAP. That brings us back to the some of the same restrictions. Part of the problem we have is we have several teams, teams that are out of control, developing modules. &lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Uncertaintly Principal and Software Engineering</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/uncertaintly-principal-and-software-engineering/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2005 23:06:14 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/uncertaintly-principal-and-software-engineering/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://scienceworld.wolfram.com/physics/UncertaintyPrinciple.html"&gt;Uncertainty Principal&lt;/a&gt; is a principle of quantum mechanics postulated by &lt;a href="http://nobelprize.org/physics/laureates/1932/"&gt;Nobel laureate&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Werner_Heisenberg"&gt;Werner Heisenberg&lt;/a&gt; in the 1920s which states that it is not possible to determine both the position and the momentum of a particle at the same instant. The reason he argued, was that the act of &amp;ldquo;observing&amp;rdquo; the particle changes its behavior with respect to what is being measured. He was one of the first scientists to bring in probability into the predictable science of physics.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Can UIs produce bugs?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/can-uis-produce-bugs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2005 18:10:30 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/can-uis-produce-bugs/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;All developers are aware how programming errors such as logic error, exception error or incorrect input data can produce bugs. But can UIs produce bugs or at least attract the user towards a bug? The answer yes! And these bugs tend to be quite difficult to catch because each user react to the UI in a different way. And the fact that programmers are so used to the behaviors of the default controls in a GUI environment it&amp;rsquo;s hard for them to test the application for UI confusions. Unfortunately this is more true in a web platform than in it is in a let&amp;rsquo;s say windows application. In a windows application the developer has more control and therefore can enforce a UI path whereas in a web-application the user is partially in control. Consider what happens in Gmail for instance, if you write an e-mail and half way through you close the browser by mistake what happens? Gmail will not give you any alerts instead the browser will close and you will have lost everything you typed (assuming you didn&amp;rsquo;t save a draft). Now let&amp;rsquo;s follow through the same steps but this time on a Windows application. Open up outlook and create a new message, now no matter how you want to close the window weather it&amp;rsquo;s closing the &amp;ldquo;New message&amp;rdquo; window or Outlook itself completely you will have to confirm that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to save the message and still quit. Now of course the example I am presenting above is obvious enough that no one makes this mistake. Everyone knows that if you are using Hotmail, Yahoo Mail or Gmail you should save your message first before quitting. But in a complex application (specially when the user is not used to it) this UI problem can get quite scary. This issue came into my attention when I released a fairly large application into production and some of the users were having trouble submiting information to us through the app. After some investigation I realized that it was the UI that was confusing some users. To make long stories short, in a web environment we as programmers must be cautious as to how to design our UIs because we have several boundaries that we have to work against, the lack of control when it comes to UI in a web environment, the statelessness of web-applications and the constant client-server connection all play a role into introducing strange bugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Object Databases (ORDBMS)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/object-databases-ordbms/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Nov 2004 19:38:02 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/object-databases-ordbms/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ORDBMS - Object Relational, Database Management system. Is an object oriented database management system. The concept at first is a bit suprising since relational database sort of by definition negates the concept of objects. In theory a relational database is a set of relation R; each table, formally known as relations, can be joined (cartesian product) to produce a new relation (which is an improper subset of R1xR2). There are many problems with this scenario. Lets say you want a database that contains sets of points where computers are physically located in a global positioning system. This hypothetical organization contains various departments, a set of departments makes up a local-organization, and a set of local-organization makes up an organization, to make situations worst, each continent can contain several organizations; and there are seven continents. This company is so large they have branches all over the seven continents. The point of this all is to find the minimal net-cost (where cost is distance) for communication between computers. Your product is expected to answers queries of this type:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>