<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Web Development on Salman Quazi</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/tags/web-development/</link><description>Recent content in Web Development on Salman Quazi</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>Salman Quazi</managingEditor><lastBuildDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 23:45:28 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.salmanq.com/tags/web-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>5 things you probably didn't know about .NET WebSockets</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/5-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-net-websockets/</link><pubDate>Sat, 13 Apr 2013 23:45:28 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/5-things-you-probably-didnt-know-about-net-websockets/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/04/websockets.png" alt="WebSockets"&gt; As most of you probably already know WebSocket provides full-duplex communication over a single TCP connection. .NET 4.5 added support for WebSockets as part of the BCL. In this article I am going to talk about few of the subtleties that you need to think about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connection upgrade is somewhat expensive&lt;/strong&gt; WebSocket connections are initiated as traditional HTTP connections. The client then usually requests an &amp;ldquo;upgrade&amp;rdquo; to a WebSocket session, this upgrade process is relatively expensive. If you are interested in performance you may want to pool a set of connection that are already upgraded and use connections from the pool.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>.NET and Node.JS - Performance Comparison (Updated)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/net-and-node-js-performance-comparison/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2013 08:57:39 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/net-and-node-js-performance-comparison/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update (3/31/2013 - 11:41 PM PST):&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This article has been updated! As most readers have commented the node.js async package is not asynchronous, which is what the original article was based on. I made an assumption I should not have. I have since rerun the tests taking this into account, as well as some of the changes recommended by &lt;a href="http://guillaume86.calepin.co/dotnet-vs-nodejs-performance.html"&gt;Guillaume Lecomte&lt;/a&gt;. I have decided to update this existing post so that there&amp;rsquo;s no confusion in the future with the data. Thank you everyone for all the comments, posts and keeping me sane.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Improving Wordpress site speed on IIS</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/improving-wordpress-site-speed-on-iis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Mar 2013 19:03:14 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/improving-wordpress-site-speed-on-iis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;One of the first things I did when I started this blog was to change the way static files are cached by IIS to improve site speed. Static files are things that aren&amp;rsquo;t going to change, things like CSS, JavaScript, images, documents, and so on. With IIS this is actually quite easy to achieve, you can start by making the following change to your web.config:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-xml" data-lang="xml"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;system.webServer&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;staticContent&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;clientCache&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;cacheControlMode=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;UseMaxAge&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;cacheControlMaxAge=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;7.00:00:00&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/staticContent&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/system.webServer&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a set of file extensions that&amp;rsquo;s already mapped to staticContent - so IIS only applies this change to all static contents. Also notice that we are caching the content on the client side. This means returning visitors will see a performance boost and we cache it for 7 days on the client side. If you have file extensions that are not part of the standard staticContent extension list, you can easily add it by doing:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part III</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-iii/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2013 06:39:59 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-iii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;We are at the finale of this three part series. &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/"&gt;In part I&lt;/a&gt; we discussed the MVVM design pattern, &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/"&gt;in part II&lt;/a&gt; we looked at the overall architecture and how the server side fits into the picture. In this article we are going to look at the client side of this and close with some final thoughts. The best place to start with the client is the HTML - so here&amp;rsquo;s the part of the HTML that&amp;rsquo;s interesting:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>IE Compatibility and W3C Validation</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/ie-compatibility-and-w3c-validation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2013 08:17:23 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/ie-compatibility-and-w3c-validation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve always been a junkie when it comes to &lt;a href="http://validator.w3.org/check?uri=http%3A%2F%2Fsalmanq.com%2F&amp;amp;charset=%28detect+automatically%29&amp;amp;doctype=Inline&amp;amp;group=0&amp;amp;user-agent=W3C_Validator%2F1.3"&gt;markup validation&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s important to me that my sites are 100% XHTML/strict compatible. But recently I came across a situation that I thought I simply couldn&amp;rsquo;t get around. In this article I am going to show you how you can add the X-UA-Compatible attribute and at the same time validate your pages through W3C validation. My website had the following tag:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;meta&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;http-equiv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;X-UA-Compatible&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;IE=edge,chrome=1&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;This is a way to force IE to not display the compatibility mode button in the URL. Which I don&amp;rsquo;t want anyway. While the X-UA-Compatible is a standard meta key, the value IE=edge is not, and therefore the validator gave me an error. So I finally figured it out, I removed the tag from my template and added the meta tag to the standard HTTP header via web.config:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part II</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Mar 2013 04:23:51 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/"&gt;Last time we looked at what the MVVM pattern was&lt;/a&gt;, and how it is used today in XAML-based applications. Today we are going to take a step further and build a mechanism to use the MVVM pattern on traditional web applications. Imagine how powerful it would be if your UI could evolve independently. We are going to build a simple web application that will display top 5 &amp;ldquo;memory intensive&amp;rdquo; processes on the server side, and here&amp;rsquo;s our basic architecture: &lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2013/03/mvvm-web-pattern.png" alt="MVVM Architecture for Web Applications"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using the MVVM pattern on web applications – Part I</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Feb 2013 09:01:15 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-the-mvvm-pattern-on-web-applications-part-i/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In this series I will be discussing how the MVVM pattern can be used for almost any type of web application. MVVM (a variant on the MVP pattern) - is a really powerful pattern that can be used in UI applications. Traditionally these UI applications has been WPF and Silverlight. In this article I will show you how you can use the same principles to build web applications. With MVVM you have the following three ideas:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How to check if Integrated Windows Authentication is available?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/how-to-check-if-integrated-windows-authentication-is-available/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2011 13:13:32 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/how-to-check-if-integrated-windows-authentication-is-available/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever worked on an intranet site, you often want to know, programmatically, if a client that&amp;rsquo;s accessing your website has the ability to automatically login to your site (Integrated Windows Authentication). With Integration Windows Authentication, Windows can basically send (as a HTTP header) the currently &amp;ldquo;logged on&amp;rdquo; username. So your application can access this LOGON_USER HTTP header and go from there. I won&amp;rsquo;t get into the details of how to setup integrated windows authentication, but basically the idea is you go into IIS and for a given resource (a folder or a file) on your site you change the directory security to Integrated Windows Authentication. Once this is done, when a client visits your local site (the definition of local depends on the gateway or group policy), IE switches to the &amp;ldquo;intranet site&amp;rdquo; profile which allows the automatic authentication. That&amp;rsquo;s the broad picture. But unfortunately, if the same users visits that same website from another location, say from their home, they will end up getting the ugly NTLM authentication box - and most of the times they don&amp;rsquo;t know what to do. Partly because their experience has changed, at work they were simply &amp;ldquo;logged in&amp;rdquo; without doing anything and now they have to login and often times need to prefix their username with domain username format. That&amp;rsquo;s not good. So it&amp;rsquo;s useful to be able to find out programmatically if integrated windows authentication is available, if it is then you simply login using the integration authentication, otherwise you provide the user with a clean and simple forms authentication system. So let&amp;rsquo;s start with some JavaScript code:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rendering Step 1 of … (ASP.NET)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/rendering-step-1-of-asp-net/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Sep 2007 01:01:29 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/rendering-step-1-of-asp-net/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The MultiView control, Wizard control or even a custom panel-based control is very useful to collect large sets of data in wizard form; and it&amp;rsquo;s often useful to give visual ques to the user as to which step he/she is in. Something similar to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/09/screenshot.jpg" title="StepMaker-Screenshot"&gt;&lt;img src="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/09/screenshot.jpg" alt="StepMaker-Screenshot"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following ASP.NET code/C# allows us to build a dynamic step control which grows or shrinks automatically given the number of views you have in a MultiView control, or the number of steps in a wizard control.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Presentation on jQuery</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/presentation-on-jquery/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Jun 2007 02:32:23 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/presentation-on-jquery/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I presented a topic on jQuery at our campus web publishers meeting. Here are the &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/2007/06/cwp.zip" title="jQuery presentation (CWP)"&gt;sample pages and the PowerPoint presentation&lt;/a&gt;. I will talk more discussions on jQuery and how it has helped us to build a powerful web-application next week.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using Control Adapters</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-control-adapters/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2007 04:55:43 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-control-adapters/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;ASP.NET 2.0 introduced a new way of modifying how ASP.NET renders a control. For example, when you say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;asp:textbox&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;FirstName&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;runat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;server&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You have very limited control over how the control actually renders. You can specify a &lt;em&gt;cssclass&lt;/em&gt; to modify the look and feel, but the actual HTML rendering is limited to what&amp;rsquo;s available from the ASP.NET server attributes. For example you cannot add client-side onfocus or onblur statements. This is where Control Adapters comes in. Control adapters allows you to modify the rendering of any server control, with complete freedom.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Automatic Printing</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/automatic-printing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2005 23:42:20 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/automatic-printing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; Learn about automatic printing in a Windows platform using WScript.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Automatic printing is a subject you will find a lot of content about on the internet &amp;ndash; but most of it is useless. It&amp;rsquo;s a massive collection of try-this-try-that. I was searching for some descent content on how to do scheduled automatic printing but spent far more time that I would like to. Finally I arrive at this code:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>XMLHttp</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/xmlhttp/</link><pubDate>Sat, 11 Jun 2005 02:11:40 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/xmlhttp/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;XMLHttp is the future of web application development. It allows threaded communication between the client and the server without ever leaving the page. If more advanced JavaScript features are standardized this might mean that a web application will act and feel very much like a regular windows application. Up until now, one of the major differences between a windows application and a web application was statelessness. However, with XMLHttp this is reduced much further because a state will no longer be round-trip from the server, it will be when the user enters a page does several thousand things and leaves the page (when they leave the page the state is lost) however during those thousand events all the state will be maintainted &amp;ndash; this can be done using XMLHttp. &lt;strong&gt;So what is XMLHttp exactly?&lt;/strong&gt; XMLHttp allows XML formatted (ideally) data to be passed to a server-side page using client side script. The response from that input can then be read back using a client side script and some actions performed based on that output. Consider this scenario, let&amp;rsquo;s say you are writing a address verification system. Your boss thinks that the user shouldn&amp;rsquo;t have to pick the state because just typing in the zip code should automatically select the appropriate state. In the olden days in order to do this you would have to do a Postback on the server and check the zipcode against your database to resolve the state. With XMLHttp once the user types in the zipcode the zipcode is passed to the server to resolve the state. When the result is found the dropdown box for the state is changed to the appropriate state &amp;ndash; without ever leaving the page. Next time I will post some sample XMLHttp code and discuss this further.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The trailing slash</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/the-trailing-slash/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Apr 2005 00:47:36 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/the-trailing-slash/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Sometimes a simple change as adding a slash may improve the performance of your web-applications. Consider this: the link &lt;a href="http://www.salmanq.com"&gt;www.salmanq.com&lt;/a&gt; is slower than &lt;a href="http://www.salmanq.com/"&gt;www.salmanq.com/&lt;/a&gt; (the only difference being the trailing slash). They will both work but the latter is faster. When this link: &lt;a href="https://www.onupol.com"&gt;www.onupol.com&lt;/a&gt; is followed the web-server returns a 301 (Moved Permanently) pointing to &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/"&gt;www.salmanq.com/&lt;/a&gt; that&amp;rsquo;s one extra round trip to and from the server per link. If you have a site that&amp;rsquo;s running without the trailing slash and you have 10K+ visitors you will certainly start to feel the consequence.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Form posts and CacheControl</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/form-posts-and-cachecontrol/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2005 23:56:02 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/form-posts-and-cachecontrol/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s say you have an HTML form which posts to another page, and that page in turn posts to other page(s) (maybe even to itself). Consider what happens in a very common scenario such as this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User visits page 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Types in username and password&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Posts to page 2 (valid user)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User sorts a column in page 2 which posts the column name and the order to page 2.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Page 2 reloads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if the user pushes the back button when he/she is step 5 he/she will see one of two things: (1) Either the previous page will load (which is the behavior we would like to have) OR (2) the infamous &amp;ldquo;Warning: Page has Expired&amp;rdquo; message will appear in the screen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Option Groups</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/option-groups/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Feb 2005 01:50:47 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/option-groups/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Not many people know about this. In a HTML dropdown (select) there is a option group tag that groups your options together. For instance:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;cars&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;optgroup&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;Honda&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Honda Accord DX&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Honda Accord LX&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Honda Accord EX&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;optgroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;optgroup&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;label&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;BMW&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;BMW 530iL&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;BMW 640iL&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;BMW 740i&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;option&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;optgroup&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/optiongroup.php"&gt;run the code above&lt;/a&gt; you will &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/optiongroup.php"&gt;notice&lt;/a&gt; users can&amp;rsquo;t even select the option group (which is perfectly valid). And the automatic indendation within the sub-groups is very useful also. This feature is supported by Opera and IE browsers. The actual version details you will have to find out.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Can UIs produce bugs?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/can-uis-produce-bugs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2005 18:10:30 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/can-uis-produce-bugs/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;All developers are aware how programming errors such as logic error, exception error or incorrect input data can produce bugs. But can UIs produce bugs or at least attract the user towards a bug? The answer yes! And these bugs tend to be quite difficult to catch because each user react to the UI in a different way. And the fact that programmers are so used to the behaviors of the default controls in a GUI environment it&amp;rsquo;s hard for them to test the application for UI confusions. Unfortunately this is more true in a web platform than in it is in a let&amp;rsquo;s say windows application. In a windows application the developer has more control and therefore can enforce a UI path whereas in a web-application the user is partially in control. Consider what happens in Gmail for instance, if you write an e-mail and half way through you close the browser by mistake what happens? Gmail will not give you any alerts instead the browser will close and you will have lost everything you typed (assuming you didn&amp;rsquo;t save a draft). Now let&amp;rsquo;s follow through the same steps but this time on a Windows application. Open up outlook and create a new message, now no matter how you want to close the window weather it&amp;rsquo;s closing the &amp;ldquo;New message&amp;rdquo; window or Outlook itself completely you will have to confirm that you don&amp;rsquo;t want to save the message and still quit. Now of course the example I am presenting above is obvious enough that no one makes this mistake. Everyone knows that if you are using Hotmail, Yahoo Mail or Gmail you should save your message first before quitting. But in a complex application (specially when the user is not used to it) this UI problem can get quite scary. This issue came into my attention when I released a fairly large application into production and some of the users were having trouble submiting information to us through the app. After some investigation I realized that it was the UI that was confusing some users. To make long stories short, in a web environment we as programmers must be cautious as to how to design our UIs because we have several boundaries that we have to work against, the lack of control when it comes to UI in a web environment, the statelessness of web-applications and the constant client-server connection all play a role into introducing strange bugs.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Faster table rendering</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/faster-table-rendering/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2005 23:55:26 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/faster-table-rendering/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Unlike FireFox, Internet Explorer does not display a table until the complete table data has arrived. This can be looked at both positvely and negatively. The positives are, once the table is rendered it is not modified (width, height, positioning) because all the data has already arrived and IE can properly compute the width and height of the cells and rendered it top-down, right-to-left without making any other adjustments to the cells already displayed. This makes things look a bit better, but this approach is definetly quite slow.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Re-Useable Images</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/re-useable-images/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2005 06:03:22 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/re-useable-images/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I was working on a project last week and part of the work was to create sort of like a template / menu / footer with an opening image. Initally I was positioning the title of the page as a regular h3 but then I thought of something great (I find it to be). &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/reuseable-images/"&gt;Take a look at this page&lt;/a&gt; &amp;ndash; if you notice carefully you will see &amp;ldquo;Salman&amp;rsquo;s Blog&amp;rdquo; is just a text. This was done using absolute positioning forcing the div and text to display over the image (with 40% opacity). Absolute positioning shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be a concern in this case because it&amp;rsquo;s meant to be used as headers which are constant and therefore have a definite pixel height from the top.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Outlook’s vCalender using ASP</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/outlooks-vcalender-using-asp/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2004 03:47:28 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/outlooks-vcalender-using-asp/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As part of a continuing effort to build more functional and user-friendly products I am working on an ASP-based vCalendar concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally I was working on a training enrollment system where users could enroll/drop for a class, standby in a waiting list and things of that nature. My department has been using this product for sometime now and my boss is starting to realize that more people signup than actually showing up. One of the reason for this she argued was they are forgetting that they had a training. One way to remind them of this training is to exploit Outlook&amp;rsquo;s reminder system.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Macintosh Like Light (CSS)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/macintosh-like-light-css/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2004 03:15:50 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/macintosh-like-light-css/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I was working on a new design for something at work and I came up with &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/mac-light/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; header layout. The background is separated into three images and the center image resizes to fit the content of the header information. Except the images the entire thing is done using CSS.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Performance - Part II</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2004 02:58:36 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As I &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-i"&gt;discussed last week&lt;/a&gt; setInterval in general gives better performance compared to setTimeout.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I will discuss how in order to improve performance, one thread can be used to run multiple animations. Multiple animations come up in several scenarios. For instance, if you have a menu that does some animation onmouseover then although not clear at first this menu system could be running multiple animations at the same time. For example, let&amp;rsquo;s say the animation takes 2 secs to run. Then in this 2 second time frame if the user highlights another menu item then the browser is actually running to threads one for each menu item. This is can bring down the performance of the system quite heavily.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Performance - Part I</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-i/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Oct 2004 02:34:33 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-performance-part-i/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This is the first in a series of articles I plan to write on improving performance in JavaScript heavy web-applications. More specifically I will discuss some of the ways you can improve on JavaScript based animations, reducing object chains, cross-browser DOM, clever ways of writing/designing objects and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improving on Animations&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No matter what type of animation it is if it&amp;rsquo;s written using JavaScript it&amp;rsquo;s most likely going to make use of setTimeout or setInterval. Both of these function work like a timeline in Flash and therefore it&amp;rsquo;s ideal for doing animations. To begin with setInterval is much faster than setTimeout. The reason is setInterval causes a function to continously run until it&amp;rsquo;s stopped using clearInterval, where as setTimeout runs a function after a given time and stops; therefore if you wanted to animate something using setTimeout you would somehow have to keep calling setTimeout (until the animation ended) where as in setInterval this is done only once. The down-side of this is setInterval is supported only by Internet Explorer so to get &lt;strong&gt;really&lt;/strong&gt; high performance you might want to write one version (separate files) of your JavaScript that&amp;rsquo;s geard towards Internet Explorer and another for Netscape (which supports setTimeout). &lt;em&gt;Next time I will discuss how to run multiple animations at once using one-thread (or one setTimeout or setInterval).&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Using XSLT to view graphical poll results</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-xslt-to-view-graphical-poll-results/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2004 04:18:47 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/using-xslt-to-view-graphical-poll-results/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;How I came to this is not relevant I think, so I will jump straight to the examples. The idea was to convert &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/poll-data-raw.xml"&gt;this XML document&lt;/a&gt; to produce &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/poll-results.xml"&gt;this output&lt;/a&gt;. So I set out to do it &amp;ndash; and it was finally done using &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/poll-transform.xsl"&gt;this XSLT stylesheet&lt;/a&gt;. The idea is quite basic. Count the number of &amp;lsquo;I agree&amp;rsquo; responses and store it in a variable. Count the number of &amp;lsquo;I disagree&amp;rsquo; responses and store it into another variable, and so on&amp;hellip; Once that&amp;rsquo;s done, the count values are multiplied with the expansion factor (&lt;em&gt;variable: efactor&lt;/em&gt;) and this number is set to the height of a div element. That&amp;rsquo;s all. Let&amp;rsquo;s all resolute to producing a standardized web!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Dynamic contents</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/dynamic-contents/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Aug 2004 03:04:04 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/dynamic-contents/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Generating dynamic contents can be a great way to allow your users to find information quickly. In &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/dynamic-index.php"&gt;this example&lt;/a&gt; the page headlines menu option was created dynamically (using JavaScript). In this case the contents was generated dynamically using H3 tags it can be very easily modified to read H1,H2, IMG, IFRAME, SPAN, DIV or any other tag that comes to mind (except perhaps BR :-))&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Date Format (using XSLT)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/date-format-using-xslt/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2004 22:31:59 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/date-format-using-xslt/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;It was sort of surprising to find out that XSLT does not have any predefined date formatting function. So after spending sometime on my own I came up with this solution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-xslt" data-lang="xslt"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:template&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;format-date&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:param&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;date&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;monthName&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;substring-before($date, &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;)&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;day&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;substring-before(substring-after($date, &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;), &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;)&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;year&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;substring-after(substring-after($date, &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;), &amp;#39;/&amp;#39;)&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:variable&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;month&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;substring(substring-after(&amp;#39;01Jan02Feb03Mar04Apr05May06Jun07Jul08Aug09Sep10Oct11Nov12Dec&amp;#39;, $monthName), 1, 3)&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:value-of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;concat($month, &amp;#39;, &amp;#39;, $year)&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;You can call this function like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-xslt" data-lang="xslt"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:call-template&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;format-date&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:with-param&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;date&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;select&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;@date&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;xsl:call-template&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;code&gt;@date&lt;/code&gt; is the date string (in this case the date attribute) you want to format. For instance this XSLT function rewrites dates written in this format: 06/23/2004 to. Jan. 2004. If you want to include the day in the resulting date, just modify the &lt;code&gt;xsl:value-of&lt;/code&gt; concat line and concat the day also.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>JavaScript Buffering - Offscreen</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-buffering-offscreen/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jul 2004 14:39:12 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/javascript-buffering-offscreen/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Just before I go to bed I thought I make an interesting post. The other day I worked on a site for a client; like most of my sites it was very heavy on style sheet (meaning most of the alignments and things were done with style sheet rather than tables, etc.) So what would happen is the page would load without style sheet for a sec. and then the style sheet would be applied. So for a split second the client would have to see the page without the style sheet &amp;ndash; which doesn&amp;rsquo;t look professional.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sequential Preloading..</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/sequential-preloading/</link><pubDate>Fri, 25 Jun 2004 14:45:49 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/sequential-preloading/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;How do you make certain JavaScript sequentially preloads your images? For instance if you have 10 images and the size of image 9 is the smallest then it&amp;rsquo;s most likely JavaScript (internet explorer rather) will load image 9 first. Then the second smallest or perhaps in no true order. However there are times when you need to make certain the images are loaded in sequence&amp;hellip;. The following accomplishes this &amp;ndash; figured it out after a lot of problems:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Speaking about events technically</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/speaking-about-events-technically/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2004 05:31:16 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/speaking-about-events-technically/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The other day I was working on something in JavaScript and I thought I would share that with you. Before I can begin though I have to describe the scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an image in an HTML page (lets call it: MyImage). I dynamically attach an event to the Image&amp;rsquo;s onload method. Due to other events on the page MyImage&amp;rsquo;s SRC attribute gets changed to something else. Now logically the onload event should execute again once the new SRC element gets loaded. But guess what? It doesn&amp;rsquo;t. onload is known as a: &amp;ldquo;recursive descent&amp;rdquo; event meaning it descends recursively from the BODY; so unless the BODY&amp;rsquo;s onload event doesn&amp;rsquo;t change (which doesn&amp;rsquo;t happen until reload/refresh) MyImage&amp;rsquo;s onload event does not fire.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Unique Elements (in XSLT)</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/unique-elements-in-xslt/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 May 2004 23:58:32 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/unique-elements-in-xslt/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;At work I have this XML document that lists all the employees along with their responsiblities. The general format looks something like this (staff.xml):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-xml" data-lang="xml"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;ga-staff&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;department&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;title=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;Administration&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Director, Corporate Accounting&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;email&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/email&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;Manager&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/responsibility&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/name&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/phone&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;email&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;...&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/email&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/employee&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/department&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;department&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;title=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; ...
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt; &lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/department&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;&amp;lt;/ga-staff&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was asked to generate a flat (meaning only their name, phone and e-mail) output (sorted by name) of all the staffs in our department. The only problem with using (existing) staff.xml is that there are certain employees who have multiple responsiblities, so their name appears more than once. Of course I cannot display their name more than once in the flat output. That makes no sense. The output would be something like this:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>CSS: word-wrap</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/css-word-wrap/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2004 23:58:46 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/css-word-wrap/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;You will notice this blog site will not overflow in the x-direction no matter what resolution you view this site in (I tried upto 640x480). When you have a div area and you are using PRE or XMP to view formatted contents (like I do in this page to view code) within that div &amp;ndash; this would be almost impossible to do. Here&amp;rsquo;s the reason: unless otherwise stated a PRE or an XMP is displayed as is. Take a look at &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/longpre.php"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt; for instance. See how it overflows? If you had a shorter viewing area the overflow would be even greater. The solution is to explicitly say to allow word breaks. Take a look at &lt;a href="https://www.salmanq.com/sources/longpre-fixed.php"&gt;this page&lt;/a&gt;. It does not overflow anymore (assuming you are using IE). View the code to see the difference.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hiding Elements During Printing</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/hiding-elements-during-printing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2004 02:15:13 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/hiding-elements-during-printing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;I work in an environment where my collegues surrounding me strongly believe there is no difference between &amp;ldquo;Microsoft Excel&amp;rdquo; and the web. One of the arguments I almost always hear: &amp;ldquo;&amp;hellip;why can&amp;rsquo;t you do it? it can be done in excel &amp;ndash; see!&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s how it all started; Excel apparently has a feature that allows a user to hide certain elements from the spreadsheet during print-out; I am not sure how exactly it&amp;rsquo;s done, I am not an Excel expert.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>AccessKey</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/accesskey/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Mar 2004 21:58:23 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/accesskey/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Almost all HTML/XHTML tags have an attribute called: accesskey. What this does is allows the programmer to assign key-codes to elements in the page. For instance, if I did this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre tabindex="0" class="chroma"&gt;&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html"&gt;&lt;span class="line"&gt;&lt;span class="cl"&gt;Search: &lt;span class="p"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nt"&gt;input&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;text&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;Search&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;value&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="na"&gt;access&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#34;S&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Then the user could enter: ALT+S to jump to this field no matter where they are on the page. This feature can make a web-site very user friendly. For instance to jump to search field on this page enter: ALT+4.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Verifying your site is running?</title><link>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/verifying-your-site-is-running/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Mar 2004 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate><author>Salman Quazi</author><guid>https://www.salmanq.com/blog/verifying-your-site-is-running/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This question often comes up-how do you make sure that your site is running? One solution is to run tools like &lt;a href="http://www.ipswitch.com/products/whatsup/index.asp"&gt;WhatsUp Gold&lt;/a&gt; that monitors your IIS service status, SQL service status etc. As long as these services respond as saying they are running, WhatsUp gold is happy. But unfortunately, the fact that these services are running does not mean that your website is functioning to the public. For example if you have a page that depends on an external web service, and for some reason the external web service is down, then your page will not respond and will eventually time out. To the public your site is down. WhatsUp gold is not necessarily going to check for that. I say not necessarily because it is possible to have WhatsUp gold monitor HTTP status, but that creates a strong coupling between WhatsUp gold and generic application development.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>